<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of the Fourth Commandement, deformed by popery, reformed &amp; restored to its primitive purity wherein is clearely proved by Scripture, arguments, and reasons, that the seventh day of the week, and not the first, viz. the day called Saturday (and not the day called Sunday) is the true Christian Sabbath ... / objections answered, and the truth cleared, by Gods unworthy servant, J.O.</title>
            <author>Ockford, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O128AA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355169</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110334</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53192)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110334)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1750:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of the Fourth Commandement, deformed by popery, reformed &amp; restored to its primitive purity wherein is clearely proved by Scripture, arguments, and reasons, that the seventh day of the week, and not the first, viz. the day called Saturday (and not the day called Sunday) is the true Christian Sabbath ... / objections answered, and the truth cleared, by Gods unworthy servant, J.O.</title>
                  <author>Ockford, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 72, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Dawson, and are to be sold by Iohn Hides ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the Reader" signed: James Ockford.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Christ Church Library, University of Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sabbatarians --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110334:1"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINE OF THE FOURTH Commandement, Deformed by Popery; <hi>Reformed &amp; Reſtored to its Primitive purity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is clearely proved by Scripture, Arguments, and Reaſons, that <hi>the Seventh day of the week,</hi> and not the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the day called Saturday [and not the day called Sunday] <hi>is the true Chriſtian Sabbath,</hi> the time Inſtituted and commanded by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for the day, or time, of his publique wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in the time of the Goſpel, as it was in the time of the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objections anſwered, and the truth cleared, by Gods unworthy Servant,</hi> J. O.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God. In it thou ſhalt do no work, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p> 
               <bibl>Exod. 20.10.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man that doth this, and the Son of man which layeth hold on it, and keepeth the Sabbath from polluting of it,</p> 
               <bibl>Iſa. 56.2</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Be doers of the word, &amp; not hearers only, deceiving your own ſelvs.</p> 
               <bibl>Jam. 1.22.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For not the hearers of the law are juſtified before God, but the doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified,</p> 
               <bibl>Rom. 2.13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Dawſon,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Hides</hi> in <hi>Blew Anchre Alley</hi> neer <hi>Pauls Alley.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:110334:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110334:2"/>
            <head>The Author to his Booke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OE little Book perform thy work, thou mayeſt be blamed, but not ſhamed; thou wilt meet with Enimies, feare not, <hi>for there are more with us, then with them,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.16.</p>
            <p>I would not intrude thee into the world in an obſcure, or doubtfull Cauſe, becauſe of many inconveniences that might inſue.</p>
            <p>But thou carrieſt with thee, the abſolute <hi>truth of God,</hi> conteined in his written law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8, 9, 10, 11. In which regard thou art aſſiſted and defended with the <hi>whole armour of righteouſneſſe,</hi> the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed truth of God, revealed <hi>by Moſes, and the Prophets, and by Jeſus Chriſt, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> againſt all aſſaults of thy Enemies. If any reprove me becauſe of thee, I deſire it may be in love, without racking my words, or perverting my meaning; but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as the matter lyeth, granting, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the particular aſſertions herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that the Impartiall reader may
<pb facs="tcp:110334:3"/>
profit thereby; and not with ſcoffes, or reproachfull terms: If any ſo doe let it be a ſigne to all men, that he maintaineth a bad Cauſe with an ill Conſcience; and that the truth ſtandeth with me and not with him. Goe, goe, and cauſe all men to know, that <hi>the Law of God is perfect, Exod.</hi> 20. and that there is no unneceſſary thing required by any Expreſſion therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. In which regard make known, I ſay, that we, and all men, are as abſolutely bound [in love] to the literall Expreſſion of the fourth Commandement, as we are to the literall Expreſſion of either the 1, 2, or 3. <hi>Commandements</hi> of that law, or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of the Six: To the end that God may be duly honoured, and our obedience to his holy law enlarged. As alſo to the end that our non-conformity to the law of God in working when we are to reſt, and our reſting when we are for to work, may not be <hi>an obſtruction to the Jewes converſion,</hi> which is the thing I deſire may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by thee. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be proſperous, ſo be it, The bleſſing of Iehovah go with thee, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>For the Lord is well pleaſed for his righteouſneſſe ſake, that he may magnifie the Law, and exalt it, <bibl>Iſay 42.21.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110334:3"/>
            <head>To the diſcreet and ſincere Reader, be Salvation in the way of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VT of a true Devotion to God, and ſincere affection to thee; I have preſented to thy conſideration, a Duty, which my Conſcience telleth me, thou oughteſt to perform to the Lord thy God, for the furtherance of his honour and thy ſalvation. Namely, the duty of <hi>Obſervation, and Sanctification of the Lords ſeventh day-Sabbath</hi> [the day called Saturday] com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Lord himſelf, <hi>Exod. 20.8.</hi> Which duty we and our Fathers have neglected neer <hi>1300. Yeers.</hi> Yea, and rejected it as a ceremoniall Element, or beggerly Rudiment. And therefore we may well complaine with the <hi>Prophet Jeremy, 3.25. We lye down in confuſion, for our ſhame covereth us, for we have ſinned againſt the Lord our God, we and our Fathers from our youth unto
<pb facs="tcp:110334:4"/>
this day and have not obeyed the voyce of the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth of this doth clearly appeare in this enſuing Subject; Therefore I deſire thee to read it with an honeſt and good Heart, without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallity, and conſider what is ſaid in it, before thou blameſt it, or cenſureſt me; leaſt thou <hi>ſpeak good of evill, and evill of good, and bring woe upon thy ſelfe, Iſay 5.20.</hi> For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is no man knoweth ſo much, but he may know more; and no man ſo perfect, but that he may erre. Therefore, <hi>ponder the path of thy feet, and let all thy wayes be ordered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; turne not to the right hand, nor to the left, but remove thy foot from evill,</hi> Prov. 4.26, 27.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy ſoules well-wiſhing friend. <hi>JAMES OCKFORD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110334:4"/>
            <head>The Doctrine of the Fourth COMMANDEMENT, Deformed by Popery; Reformed and Reſtored to its Primitive PURITIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP I.</hi> The Decalogue is Morall and perpetuall, nothing is to be added thereto, nor diminiſhed from it.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Law,</hi> whereof I Treat, of which the <hi>Fourth Commandement is</hi> a part, was given of God on <hi>Mount Sinai, Exod.</hi> 19. &amp; 20. <hi>Cap.</hi> And <hi>written with his owne Finger in Tables of Stone,</hi> Exod. 31.18. Deut. 5.22. <hi>The Effect</hi> of which Heavenly Law was engraven in nature at mans Creation, which Divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe remaineth in the nature of man, and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to doe in ſome meaſure, that which God by the Law of the Letter requireth of him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14 &amp; 15. Although the cuſtome of ſinning, and the deceitfulneſſe of mans heart, hath blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110334:5"/>
ſtained and darkned in him, that which we ought to diſcerne, know, and doe: But ſuch is the Mercy and Goodneſſe of God unto us, that he hath not left us without a plaine Demonſtration <hi>of His holy Will by His holy Law, the Decalogue;</hi> which <hi>Holy Law</hi> bindeth us to all Duties tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to life and Godlineſs.<note n="*" place="margin">As this Law bound the Jews to all duties commanded in the time of the Law, <hi>Deut. 6.5.</hi> Even ſo it bindeth us, and all men, to all duties commanded by the Goſpel. The reaſon is, becauſe he that obeyeth not the Goſpel, loveth not the Lord his God with all his heart, and with all his ſoule, and with all his mind; as the Law, by the mouth of Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel, requireth of us, <hi>Mat. 22.37.</hi>
                  </note> Which Decalogue, or Morall Law, remaineth abſolutely unchangeable, as it appeareth by the words of the Prophet, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 111. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7, 8, 9. where he alluding to the Law written in <hi>Tables of Stone,</hi> (ſpeaking of God) ſaith, <hi>The Worke of His Hands are Veritie and Judgment: All his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements are ſure, they ſtand faſt for ever and ever, &amp;c.</hi> A note of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall unchangeableneſſe. And in this regard, they are ſaid to be <hi>Faithfull, Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>ver.</hi> 86. Yea, <hi>Righteous, and very Faithfull, verſ.</hi> 138.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Law,</hi> is <hi>Gods Covenant, Exod.</hi> 19.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.13. which God hath given to man to be obſerved <hi>for ever, Deu.</hi> 4.9.10. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.37. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29 29. <hi>without adding to it, or diminiſhing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110334:5"/>
ought from it,</hi> Deut 4.2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.23. Eccleſ. 3.14. Prov. 30.6. Gal. 3.15.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Law,</hi> or <hi>Covenant,</hi> conſiſteth of Ten <hi>Precepts, Sentences, or Words, Exod.</hi> 20, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.19.</p>
               <p>Which <hi>Precepts, Sentences, or Words,</hi> are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably joyned together: Comparatively, as a Chaine of ten links; Or as a compleat name, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of ten Syllables, or Letters; So that if one Link be broken, the whole Chaine is broken; If one Syllable, or Letter, be removed, or changed, the whole name is altered, changed, or broken.</p>
               <p>Even ſo it ſtandeth with the Law of Gods <hi>Ten Commandements;</hi> for when one Precept hath been tranſgreſſed, or broken, (yea, of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> by name) God hath reproved the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders for breaking <hi>of His Commandements, Exod.</hi> 16.28. That one Act of Tranſgreſſion, is the breach of <hi>Gods Law, or Covenant.</hi> See I pray <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.2, 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.4. This truth St. <hi>James</hi> knew well, and would have us to know it alſo; and therefore he ſaith, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Whoſoever keepeth the whole Law, and faileth in one point, is guilty of all.</hi> And his Reaſon is, <hi>Becauſe he that ſaid, Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery, ſaid alſo, Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> Now (ſaith he) <hi>If thou commit not Adultery,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110334:6"/>
yet if thou Kill, thou art become a Tranſgreſſour of the Law,</hi> verſ. 11.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour treating of this <hi>Law</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.19. ſaith: <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall breake one of theſe leaſt Commandements, and ſhall teach men ſo, ſhall be called leaſt in the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Note, I pray, theſe words of our Saviour are grounded upon a Two-fold Reaſon: The one is, becauſe in <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. He had made known to his Diſciples, <hi>That he came not to deſtroy the Law or Propets, but to fulfill them.</hi> The ſecond Reaſon is, becauſe in <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. He had ratified e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very jot and tittle of the Law, till all things be fulfilled; <hi>to wit,</hi> to the end of the World.</p>
               <p>Thus was Gods Law ratified for Inſtruction of obedience to <hi>Beleevers,</hi> in the time of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> according to the Propheſie of old, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.16.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour, to poſſeſs our minds of the truth of this in <hi>Luke</hi> 16.17. He ſaith, <hi>It is eaſier for Heaven and Earth to paſſe away, than one tittle of the Law to faile.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>deceive not your ſelves,</hi> nor let any deceive you, and cauſe you to thinke my comming in the fleſh doth make any part of my Fathers Law void; for I aſſure you, Heaven may ſooner, or eaſier, ceaſe to be Heaven; or the Earth may ſooner, or eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ceaſe to be Earth, than any jot, or tittle of my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110334:6"/>
Fathers Law ceaſe to be of Force, in not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring obedience to my Father, according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions therein contained.</p>
               <p>This doth clearely demonſtrate, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath not abrogated the Decalogue, nor any part thereof, but ratified it to be a rule of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, for performance of duties both towards God and man, while we live on Earth: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what God hath joyned together, let no man ſeparate, nor neglect any obedience to any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion therein contained. For certainly, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath not abrogated this Law, nor any part thereof, as touching obedience; but only as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. And hence it is, that true Believers are not held under the terror and condemnation thereof, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.7.9. becauſe Jeſus Chriſt hath performed for them, that which God by the ſtrictneſs of the Law requireth of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3, 4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. And in this ſence, Jeſus Chriſt is ſaid to be the end of the Law, <hi>for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to every one that beleeveth,</hi> Rom. 10.4. And in this ſence, Believers are ſaid not to be <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, but under Grace,</hi> Rom. 6.14. As alſo, to <hi>be delivered from the Law,</hi> Chap. 7.6. And in this ſence it is ſaid, <hi>The Righteouſneſſe of God without the Law is manifeſted,</hi> Rom. 3.21.22. This grace wrought by Jeſus Chriſt for Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110334:7"/>
is not for their obedience, either to Law, or Goſpel, nor without their obedience (in ſome meaſure) to both, but by their Faith in Chriſt: Thus all thoſe, which by Faith receive the Holy Spirit, <hi>are not under the Law,</hi> Gal. 5.18. to wit, to condemne them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1, 2. Yet are they not without <hi>the Law as appertaineth to God, but in the Law through Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.21. So that although Believers are quit, freed, or delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the Curſes or Terrour of the Law, by Jeſus Chriſt; yet hath he not diſcharged, or freed them from their obedience to it: For this, read <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37.38.39. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.1.2.3. <hi>Iames</hi> 2.10.11.12. Therefore, <hi>if thou wilt enter into life, keep the Commandements,</hi> Mat. 19.17. And they are Ten, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.4.</p>
               <p>It being ſo, I doe not ſee how it is poſſible, that the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> or any Precept, Sentence, or Word of it, was abrogated by Jeſus Chriſt. As was Circumciſion, the Paſſeover, and Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> Sacrifices, Offerings, and burnt Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, Monthly, and Yearly Feſtivals, <hi>which were ſhadowes of good things to come,</hi> Heb. 10.1. <hi>And ſerved as a Schoolemaſter to lead men to Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.24. <hi>In whom it had its end,</hi> Coloſ. 2.11.14.15.16.17. Heb. 7.12.18.19. Epheſ. 2.14.15. But the Decalogue, nor any part thereof, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110334:7"/>
not out Jeſus Chriſt, either in Perſon, or Office; But being morall and perpetuall, it bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all men, in all ages, to the duties therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, or contained, both in body and Spirit: <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as Jewes; <hi>Believers,</hi> and Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5 <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37.38.39. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.9. <hi>For God is not the God of the Jewes only, but of the Gentiles alſo,</hi> Rom. 3.29. Now, ſeeing God requireth obedience of all men unto it, it followeth, Jeſus Chriſt by his fulfilling of it, hath not delivered, or diſcharged us from our obedience to it.</p>
               <p>I doubt not, but moſt men devoted to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, will aſſent with me, as touching the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſecond Table of the Divine Law, that it is Morall, and bindeth every man to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular duties therein expreſſed. But few men there are as yet, that doth aſſent with me, that the Precepts of the firſt Table have ſuch authority over us, in binding us to every particular Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion therein contained. <hi>For Papiſts doe deny the ſecond Commandement, againſt worſhipping of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages to be Morall, and appertaine not to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as Mr.</hi> Brabourne <hi>ſaith (on the Sabbath Page</hi> 519) <hi>out of</hi> Polanus Syntag. <hi>page</hi> 353.</p>
               <p>Others there are, which deny the affirmative part of the third Commandement, (in that they refuſe to take an oath in any right cauſe) through
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110334:8"/>
a miſ-apprehenſion of our Saviours words, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34, 35, 36. and the words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 5.12. Yea, Papiſts, and all differing opinions among men, <hi>profeſſing Chriſt,</hi> by what name ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are called, do deny the Morality of the Fourth Commandement, or at leaſt, part thereof, in practice, though not in words; the errour of which opinion I ſhall refute by <hi>Scripture, Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Reaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But firſt I will reaſon againſt them in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the Apoſtle reaſoned againſt thoſe <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> which denied the reſurrection of the dead, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14, 15, 16, 17, 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Manifeſteth <hi>12</hi> Abſurdities which doe follow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Doctrine or Aſſertion that the Fourth Commandement, or any part thereof is abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which are not ſuitable with Godlineſſe, or with the holineſſe, truth, or integrity of the Decalogue.</head>
               <p>THe Firſt Abſurditie which doth follow on the Doctrine that the Fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is abrogated, or part thereof, is to affirme (conſequently) that there are but 9 <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110334:8"/>
in the morall Law, which expreſly ſpeaketh to us, in requiring duties of us, contrary to <hi>Exod,</hi> 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.13.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It is to affirme, that Gods Law of the <hi>ten Commandements,</hi> are not <hi>perpetually</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, the fourth ſtandeth as a <hi>Cifer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, All the duties commanded in the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue</hi> appertaineth not to us.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, God never intended that we ſhould walke in the obedience thereof.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, Jeſus Chriſt nor his Apoſtles, never taught us ſo to doe; nor never ratified any ſuch thing for us to obſerve, contrary to <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, It is no rule of <hi>righteous</hi> walking for us.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, It is not for us the way to walke in to obtain <hi>Juſtification by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eightly, It hath not a correſpondency with the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, It taught the <hi>Jewes</hi> to worke ſix dayes, ſucceſſively, from the Creation, and to reſt the ſeventh, after Gods example; which thing we ought not to doe contrary to <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.11.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, He that followeth the literall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the <hi>decalogue,</hi> or morrall law, erreth.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, For any to ſay, we are not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſeventh day Sabbath, becauſe the duty
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110334:9"/>
thereof is abrogated; It is to affirme, that Gods law is changed, contrary to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.7. &amp; 8.</p>
               <p>Twelfly, Thoſe which affirme the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath,</hi> was to be kept before our Saviours Death, and Reſurrection, and is not to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſince by Chriſtians: doe thereby avouch, that <hi>Gods Teſtimonies, his Law, his Covenant, is Yea, and Nay;</hi> contrary to the nature of Gods Law, and many texts of Scripture. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.138, 142, 152. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.2. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</p>
               <p>If theſe, and the like aſſertions, may not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for truth, but rejected for errour, by all men profeſſing Chriſtianity and the feare of God; then all men profeſſing Chriſtianity and the feare of God, are for ever to confeſſe, that the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> and every jot, and title thereof is morall, and remaineth in force, and bindeth all men as unchangeably, to the obſervation of the ſeventh day-Sabbaths, ſince our Saviours Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as ever it did any men before his Aſcenſion.</p>
               <p>In which regard I profeſſe in the feare or God, I doe not ſee but that it is as great a ſinne to doe contrary to the literall expreſſion of the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> as it is to doe contrary to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall expreſſion of either the <hi>firſt, ſecond, or third Commandements</hi> of the divine Law, except ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity hinder it: for ſure it is, <hi>Whoſoever keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110334:9"/>
the whole Law, and faileth in one point, is guilty of all,</hi> James 2.10.</p>
               <p>If this will not be aſſented unto, I deſire to know of him that will oppoſe me, whether our Saviour in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18. did ratifie the Decalogue, or Law of ten Commandements, to remain till all things be fulfilled, yea, or nay? If nay, what Law was it that he ratified? If yea, then he ratified the fourth Commandement, to remaine for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to Godlineſſe,</hi> in the literall expreſſions thereof, as unchangeable as to any other expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that law; If any will deny it, let him ſhew how our Saviour did ratifie the whole Law, yea, every <hi>jot and title</hi> of it, and did not ratifie the fourth Commandement, which is a tenth part of that law, which conſiſteth of more then 80. words. And if our Saviour ratified the fourth Commandement, I deſire to know why it ought not to be as conſcionably obſerved, as any of the other nine Commandements; but if any ſay, it was repealed again by Chriſt, let him ſhew how he could doe it, and <hi>not diminiſh any thing from the morall Law:</hi> As alſo, when he did it, and what are his words of repealing it, and then alſo, prove it was no part of the Law which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles eſtabliſhed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. As alſo that we may omit the duty of the ſeventh day-<hi>Sabbath,</hi> and not fall under the tranſgreſſion of the Law, ſpoken of by Saint <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:110334:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Containeth <hi>10.</hi> Reaſons, demonſtrating that the fourth Commandement is morall, and not cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall. Secondly, Objections anſwered.</head>
               <p>THe firſt Reaſon is, why the duty of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth dayes <hi>reſt</hi> is morall, and not ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, is becauſe it differeth in its nature from a <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall precept.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Ceremoniall precept, or precepts, was given of God, and uſed of men, to ſet forth ſome good thing to be wrought, or brought by Jeſus Chriſt, after mans fall, and the promiſe of the <hi>Meſſias, Heb.</hi> 9. <hi>chap.</hi> 10. But the ſeventh day-Sabbath, was made by Chriſt, the Word of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.2, 3. before there was any need, or uſe of any Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, <hi>Gen,</hi> 1.2, 3. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the <hi>fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is morall.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the ſeventh dayes reſt is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, doth appeare from the Ground, or Reaſon, wherefore God gave to man the holy Sabbath, expreſſed by <hi>Moſes, Ezod.</hi> 31.17. <hi>chap.</hi> 20.11. The grounds, or reaſons being morall and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, whereon the duty was founded, it argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the perpetuity of the day it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:110334:10"/>Thirdly, That the duty of obſerving the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth dayes reſt, is morall, doth appeare from a further uſe of the day, for Gods publique wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to be performed on it, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.14, 15, 42. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16, 31. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.13. The uſefulneſſe of pious duties, requireth a uſefull, and perpetuall day, and no day ſo fit as that day, which God inſtituted, bleſſed, and ſanctified, for that end; <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> the ſeventh dayes reſt is morall.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That the duty of the ſeventh dayes reſt <hi>is morall,</hi> doth appeare, by that the wilfull tranſgreſſours of it were to be put to death, by the hand of the Magiſtrate, as thoſe were which wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſgreſſed any of the other three Precepts of the firſt Table, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.15. <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.32, 35, 36. But the tranſgreſſours of Ceremoniall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, God himſelfe puniſhed them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.32, 35. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6, 7. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is <hi>morall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, The fourth Commandement was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with the other nine Precepts, with Power, Majeſty, and Terror, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. There was never a Ceremoniall precept given after that manner; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the fourth <hi>Commandement</hi> is <hi>morall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, The fourth <hi>Commandement</hi> was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in a table of ſtone, &amp; <hi>put into the Arke, Deut.</hi> 10.5. But there was no Ceremoniall precept written in a table of ſtone, nor put into the Arke,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110334:11"/>
1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the duty of the ſeventh days reſt is Morall, and not Ceremoniall. The truth of this is alſo affirmed by Dr. <hi>Bayly,</hi> in the practice of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, <hi>Pag.</hi> 159. and by Mr. <hi>Biſco,</hi> in his <hi>glorious Miſtery, page</hi> 60.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, God himſelfe kept the ſeventh day-<hi>Sabbath, Gen.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.11. Can it be ſhewn that ever God kept a Ceremoniall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept? O no! <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is an <hi>Everlaſting Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eighthly, The fourth Commandement (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Seventh day-Sabbath is commanded) is a tenth part of the <hi>Morall</hi> Law; the Law being Morall, the dutie of the ſeventh dayes reſt muſt needs be Morall alſo.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, Our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> would not that his Diſciples ſhould breake the <hi>Sabbath</hi> at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem, Mat.</hi> 24.20. which was 38 years after his Paſſion. Can it be ſhewen, that ever his will was, that his Diſciples <hi>ſhould keepe</hi> a ceremoniall Precept ſo long after his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? If any can, let them doe it, or elſe let them confeſſe the duty of the ſeventh dayes reſt is Morall.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, and laſtly, If the duty of the ſeventh day-<hi>Sabbath</hi> is abrogated, then it is not meet nor fit that it ſhould ſtand in Pariſh Churches, or publique Aſſemblies with the other nine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Morall Law; for as it ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110334:11"/>
with, or amongſt thoſe Morall Precepts, it reacheth, and commandeth obedience to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſeventh dayes-Sabbath, (the day cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Saturday, which men ſay is abrogated) as expreſly, and as abſolutely, as the <hi>Firſt, Second,</hi> or <hi>Third</hi> Commandements of that <hi>Law</hi> doe teach the expreſſe duties commanded in them, or any other of the 6 Commandements doth teach that which is expreſſed in them.</p>
               <p>But indeed, and in truth, the dutie of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth dayes-Sabbath, commanded in the fourth Commandement, <hi>is Morall and Perpetuall,</hi> as any of the other 9 <hi>Commandements,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth as abſolutely binde us, and all men, to the due obedience thereof, as any of the other nine do to the duties expreſſed in them: Therefore it is meet and fit it ſhould ſtand with the other nine Commandements, to teach men their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the <hi>ſeventh dayes-Sabbath,</hi> to wit, the day called <hi>Saturday,</hi> for that indeed is <hi>the Sabbath of the Lord thy God,</hi> whereon he hath forbid thee to do any ſervile work, as hath been ſhewn; which duty all men are <hi>enjoyned</hi> unto untill the end of the World, for till then the Sabbath ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.23, 24. <hi>Ergo,</hi> its Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Perpetuall.</p>
               <p>If the Fourth Commandement be an abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Ceremony,</hi> and therefore we are not to walk in the obedience thereof; then we are as really
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110334:12"/>
diſcharged from working 6 dayes, as we are from reſting the ſeventh: And if it be ſin to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſeventh day-Sabbath, becauſe the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Commandement is abrogated, which command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; then it is ſinne alſo to worke 6 dayes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the fourth Commandement is abrogated, which commanded it.</p>
               <p>The reaſon is, becauſe when any Ceremoniall Precept, or Precepts, were abrogated, every part or branch thereof, was abrogated alſo, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11, 12. <hi>Exod</hi> 12.3, 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, if it be errour to ſay, mens working ſix dayes is abrogated; then it is errour to ſay, mens reſting the ſeventh day is abrogated, or done away.</p>
               <p>Evident it is, by that which is already ſaid, the <hi>Decalogue being Morall,</hi> the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement being part of the Decalogue, is Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall alſo. It being ſo, let him that will oppoſe me, prove that it is our duty to doe ſervile work on the ſeventh day, called Saturday, if he can: But if he cannot ſhew me any Precept for it, then let him ſhew me what diſpenſation there is vouchſafed to men to doe common worke on the Lords ſeventh day-Sabbath, and who it was which firſt granted the diſpenſation: This doe, and faile not, or elſe ceaſe from a <hi>weekly propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of the Lords ſeventh day-<hi>Sabbaths.</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, for my part, I believe the Morall Law ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110334:12"/>
knowne unto us the minde, or will of God, concerning our duty, both towards Himſelf, and our Neighbour. And therefore, I ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I had not known luſt, if the Law had not ſaid, Thou ſhall not covet,</hi> Rom. 7.7.</p>
               <p>In like manner, I ſay, I had not knowne I ſhould not <hi>have other Gods before God, had not the Law ſo ſaid,</hi> Exod. 20.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neither had I knowne I ſhould not make to my ſelf any Graven Image, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nor that I ſhould not bow downe, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them, had not the Law forbid it,</hi> Exod. 20.5.</p>
               <p>Neither had I known that it is my duty <hi>to keep ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſeventh day-Sabbath (to wit, the day called Saturday) whereon no work is to be done,</hi> had not God by his Law commanded the one, and forbid the other, <hi>Exod</hi> 20.8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
               <p>O know, and believe, the Precepts of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law ſpeaketh as well to thee, as to me. Haſt thou endeavoured to walke in the obedience of the 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Commandements <hi>of Gods Law?</hi> and haſt thou wholy neglected thy duty to the fourth Commandement, in not keeping holy the ſeventh day-Sabbath? and haſt thou done ſervile work thereon, which thing God hath foabidden thee? If yea, ſurely thou art a tranſgreſſor of Gods Law. Be inſtructed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and repent of Sabbath-breaking, and for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110334:13"/>
time to come, keep holy the Sabbath day, the day called Saturday, and doe no work thereon, <hi>thou, nor thy ſonne, nor thy daughter, thy man-ſervant, nor thy maid-ſervant, thy cattell, not the ſtranger that is n within thy Gates, &amp;c. for it is the Will of God that they ſhould reſt as well as thou,</hi> Deut. 5.14</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For, Whatſoever the Law ſaith, it ſaith to them that are under it,</hi> Rom. 3.19. <hi>Thou art under it, and not above it, therefore thou ought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt not to tranſgreſſe it, for the Law hath domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion over a man as long as he liveth,</hi> Rom. 7.1. Therefore, if thou wilt not be condemned by it, conform unto it: <hi>For, whoſoever committeth ſin, tranſgreſſeth alſo the Law,</hi> 1 John 3.4. Yea, ſurely, the <hi>ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the Law,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.56.</p>
               <p>Therefore, deceive not thy ſelfe, nor let any deceive thee, or cauſe thee to beleeve, that it was ſinne to doe any thing contrary to the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> before our Saviours Death and Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that it is not ſo now, but that <hi>Chriſtian men</hi> may doe ſomething which God by <hi>His Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law</hi> doth forbid, and not ſin.</p>
               <p>Certainly, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> nor his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> hath not left Chriſtians any ſuch diſpenſation. Errour therefore it is for any to affirme, that they may doe ſervile worke on the Lords ſeventh day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, (where neceſſity is not) contrary to his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110334:13"/>
Holy Law, and not ſinne. Therefore, know, and beleeve, that as the Morall Law was <hi>Holy, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, Juſt,</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> before our Saviour came in the Fleſh, and taught men their duty toward God, and man, in an unerring way: Even ſo, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law is <hi>Holy, Righteous, Juſt, and Good,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince our Saviour came in the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us our duties toward God and man in a right and <hi>unerring way,</hi> and ſo it ſhall for <hi>ever. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if thou wilt enter into life, keepe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi> Matth. 19.17. And they are ten, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.4.</p>
               <p>As I would not be miſtaken in any thing, I deſire I may not be miſtaken in this; <hi>viz.</hi> for any to thinke I meane men may obtaine <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe to juſtification</hi> by the works of the Law: Oh no, that I doe not, that <hi>is impoſſible, Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.10.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. Errour it is to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> or any elſe, that expect to receive Righteouſneſſe by, or for their obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; But I preſſe men to the obedience of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men cannot be ſaved without obedience to it, in ſome meaſure, through faith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. But I doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in my heart, and confeſſe with my mouth, that <hi>juſtification to ſalvation,</hi> is freely beſtowed on the Beleever wholy undeſerved. It is not of workes, <hi>but by Grace through Faith, that men are ſaved; and not of our ſelves, it is the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110334:14"/>
gift of God,</hi> Epheſ. 2.8. 2 Tim. 1.9.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel, publiſhed by Jeſus Chriſt, brought not a new way of Righteouſneſſe and Salvation into the World, which was not ſpoken of, or taught before in the <hi>Law and Prophets, John</hi> 5.46, 47. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Beza</hi> in his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent on <hi>Mat. 5.17.</hi>
                  </note>But it is a fuller manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Law and Prophets; ſo that our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to the Decalogue, is not deſtructive, or prejudiciall to our obedience to the Goſpel, but highly advanceth it: <hi>For the Law is not againſt the Promiſe of God,</hi> Gal. 3.21. Neither is the Goſpel contrary to the Law, for the preaching of faith doth eſtabliſh it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. Yea, ſuch is the <hi>Vnion</hi> betweene the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that the ſame <hi>words</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> uſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand obedience to God by the Law, in the time of the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5. the ſame words our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour uſeth in the Goſpel, to command obedience to God, according to the Law, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22 37. Yea, ſuch Union and communion there is between the Law and the Goſpel, that as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſendeth us to be inſtructed by Chriſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22. Even ſo <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſendeth us to be inſtructed by <hi>Moſes, John</hi> 5.39.46.47. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.29.31. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.</p>
               <p>It being ſo, it followeth, that ſeeing by the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110334:14"/>
Law me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re commanded to keepe a <hi>holy reſt,</hi> and to abſtaine from <hi>ſervile work</hi> on the <hi>ſeventh day;</hi> the Goſpel doth not ſay nay. Thou ſhalt keep a holy reſt, and abſtaine from ſervile work on the firſt day of the week: Oh no, there is no ſuch word; therefore, ſure it is, the ſelfe ſame Law which commanded men to keep a holy reſt on the ſeventh day, in the time of the Law, the ſelfe ſame Law requireth us to keepe a holy reſt on the ſeventh day in the time of the Goſpel. Therefore, <hi>Remember to keepe holy the Sabbath day,</hi> the day called <hi>Saturday,</hi> the ſeventh, and laſt day of the weeke, for that is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, which he commandeth thee to conſecrate to his Service, in worſhipping him on it, <hi>in ſpirit and truth,</hi> as the Goſpel requireth of thee, and neglect it not.</p>
               <p>As the Word of God doth manifeſt the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke to be the Sabbath; So doth both Ancient and Moderne Writers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it ſo to be. Yea, Doctor <hi>Hylyn</hi> doth affirm, in his Hiſtory of the <hi>Sabbath, par.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 62. <hi>that when ever (for a thouſand yeares and upward) we meet with</hi> Sabbatum <hi>in any Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of what name ſoever, muſt be underſtood of no other day then the Saturday. And Doctor</hi> White <hi>on the Sabbath,</hi> pag. 202. <hi>ſaith, when the Ancient Fathers diſtinguiſh, and give proper names to the particular dayes of the weeke, they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110334:15"/>
alwayes ſtile the Saturday, Sabbatum,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Saturday,</hi> the laſt day of the week is the <hi>Sabbath day;</hi> the truth thereof is confeſſed by all Judicature Courts in <hi>England;</hi> for when they write on the <hi>Saturday,</hi> the laſt day of the weeke, they ſtile it, <hi>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Sabbathi;</hi> to wit, the <hi>Sabbath day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> At the end of which <hi>Sabbath, the firſt day of the week beginneth, Mat.</hi> 28.1. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.1, 2, which is the day commonly called <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> (which is highly extolled, although there is no word of God, which commandeth the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, as now it is.)</p>
               <p>Sure it is, we know no [other] name in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for the ſeventh day, but the <hi>Sabbath day;</hi> neither know we any other name for <hi>Sunday,</hi> but the firſt day of the week; for this ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 24.1. <hi>John</hi> 20.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If it be objected, that the ſeventh day-Sabbath, was given to the <hi>Jewes</hi> only, and not to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in that the <hi>Jewes</hi> were charged with the keeping of it, in remembrance of their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance out of <hi>Egypts</hi> bondage, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.15. which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were not. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, It is true, they were delivered out of <hi>Aegypts</hi> bondage [through the great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God unto them] and thereon were enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to keep the Sabbath, as a motive to ſtir them up to a more devout obſervation thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110334:15"/>But was it ſo given to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereof doth not appertain to us, Oh no! there is no Scripture that ſo ſaith; neither doth it follow, that we owe no obedience to it, becauſe they were enjoyned to keepe it, in remembrance of their deliverance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Egypt;</hi> becauſe then it would follow, we are not enjoyned to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the other nine <hi>Commandements</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>For on the ſame ground, or conſideration, they were enjoyned to keep the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath,</hi> upon the ſame ground they were enjoyned to keep the other 9 <hi>Commandements</hi> alſo, for this ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2, 3. &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.6. <hi>chap.</hi> 7.8, 9, 10, 11. It being ſo, it followeth, If we may not omit our duty to the 9. Commandements of the morall Law, we ought not to the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement neither.</p>
               <p>Again, If men will exempt themſelves from the duty of the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath,</hi> becauſe it was given to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> then on the ſame ground, they may exempt themſelves from all duties taught by our Saviour on the <hi>Mount, Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>chap.</hi> 6, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. and alſo from all duties taught in the <hi>Epiſtle to the Hebrewes;</hi> and alſo from all duties taught by by <hi>Saint James in his Epiſtle</hi> on the ſame ground.</p>
               <p>Now if it be <hi>errour</hi> to <hi>exempt our ſelves</hi> from theſe, and many other <hi>heavenly Inſtructions,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110334:16"/>
they were given to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> then it is <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> to exempt our ſelves from the duty of the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> becauſe it was given to the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If it be further objected, the duty of the ſeventh day-Sabbath, <hi>belongeth not to us,</hi> becauſe our Saviour hath not commanded it to be obſerved in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, It is an ignorant <hi>Cavill,</hi> againſt the duty commanded in the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> becauſe our Saviour doth as abſolutely require obedience of us, to the duty of the ſeventh day-Sabbath, incluſively (in <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37, 38.39.) as he doth to the 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, and 10. Commandements of the <hi>morall Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, If it be a ſufficient plea, to exempt our ſelves from the duty of the <hi>fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> becauſe it is not expreſly repeated by our Saviour in the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> then upon the ſame conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, we may as well exempt our ſelves from the duties taught by the 1, 2, and 3, <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the ſame <hi>Law;</hi> for neither of thoſe precepts are in expreſſe words laid down by our <hi>Saviour</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> therefore, I ſay, If it be an <hi>errour</hi> to exempt our ſelves from the duties of the 1, 2, and 3. <hi>Commandements,</hi> becauſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words are not laid down by our <hi>Saviour, in the Goſpel;</hi> then <hi>errour</hi> it is, for any to exempt themſelves from the duties of the <hi>fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110334:16"/>
although the duty of it is not in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words laid downe <hi>in the Goſpel.</hi> Yea, a truth it is, <hi>Whoſoever keepeth the whole Law, and faileth in one point, is guilty of all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Antiquity and Morality, of the ſeventh day-Sabbath, which is the day to be obſerved, and not a ſeventh day inſtead of it.</head>
               <p>THe ſeventh day-<hi>Sabbath,</hi> whereof I <hi>treat,</hi> which was <hi>made for man,</hi> Mark 2.27, <hi>and given to man [Exod.</hi> 16.29.] was <hi>bleſſed and ſanctified,</hi> the <hi>firſt ſeventh day</hi> of the <hi>worlds Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, [Gen.</hi> 2.2, 3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8, 9, 10, 11.] was obeyed, and diſobeyed, <hi>before</hi> the Law was given on <hi>Mount Sinai, Exod.</hi> 16.27, 28, 30. Which <hi>Precept</hi> being repeated on the <hi>Mount,</hi> with the other <hi>nine Precepts;</hi> it had a <hi>memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> annexed it, in regard of a <hi>former neglect to it;</hi> as alſo the more to incite the <hi>Jewes, and us Gentiles,</hi> to a diligent obſervation thereof, for time to come.</p>
               <p>This ſeventh day <hi>God inſtituted,</hi> and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be a <hi>ſelected,</hi> or <hi>peculiar</hi> time, for his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.21.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Sabbath our Saviour unviolably kept,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110334:17"/>
and ſpent in the <hi>adminiſtration of the Word,</hi> Luke 4.16, 31. Mark 6.2. and in other holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>charity, glorifying his Father by Miracles, Mat.</hi> 12.9, 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.8, 9.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Sabbath</hi> our <hi>Saviours Diſciples</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved after his death, to Gods honour and their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>laudable memoriall:</hi> For it is recorded of them, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.56. That they reſted the ſeventh day, according to the Commandement. Yea, it evidently apeareth, that the <hi>Apoſtles and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Gentiles as well as Jewes,</hi> conſtantly ſpent the ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbaths,</hi> in <hi>holy and religious exerciſe.</hi> For this ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 13.14, 15, 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> 27, 42, 43, 44. <hi>chap</hi> 16.13, 14. <hi>chap.</hi> 17.2, 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 24.14.<note n="*" place="margin">The like inſtance can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhewne in the new Teſtament, that either the Apoſtles, or Diſciples did thus conſtantly aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on the firſt day of the week.</note> Yea, ſome <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches obſerved it, for more then the ſpace 400. <hi>yeares</hi> after <hi>Chriſt;</hi> of this <hi>Socrates</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes us, <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>chap.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Yea, albeit the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was one of the <hi>firſt Churches</hi> [or rather the firſt] which <hi>diſcerted the ſeventh day-Sabbath;</hi> yet they kept it a certain ſpace of time, after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of the Apoſtles. For <hi>Juſtin Martyr living in Rome,</hi> about the yeare 150. ſaith <hi>[Apologie, ſecond pro] The manner was on the Sabbath day when the people were gathered together, to have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110334:17"/>
the Scriptures read in the publique congregation in the time of publique prayer, the ſpace of a whole hower;</hi> as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Whitguift</hi> hath it in his Booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Cartwright, pag.</hi> 578.</p>
               <p>Yea, I finde by <hi>Socrates, Eccle. hiſt. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. that for the ſpace of 200. <hi>yeares,</hi> almoſt, all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches, throughout <hi>the whole world,</hi> did keep every <hi>Sabbath-day after other,</hi> whereon they did adminiſter the miſteries of our Saviour (or Sacraments) <hi>except Rome and Alexandria, who of an old tradition did not uſe it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Which <hi>holy Sabbath</hi> ought to have been ſpent in <hi>holy exerciſe</hi> to this time; yea, and for <hi>ever, Exod.</hi> 31.17. <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.23.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath</hi> ought to have been kept, and ſpent in the <hi>worſhip</hi> and <hi>ſervice of God.</hi> Severall men of note, doth confeſſe the truth thereof; although their practice anſwered not with it, no, nor their words at ſome times neither: And therefore I looke upon their Expreſſions, as <hi>juſtifying the truth</hi> againſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I will beginne with Mr, <hi>Beza</hi> in his margent, on <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. who ſaith, <hi>Since God permitteth ſix dayes to our laboures, that we ought willingly, to dedicate the ſeventh, to ſerve him, wholly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Mr. <hi>Perkins on Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. ſaith, <hi>Six dayes thou ſhalt labour, and the ſeventh
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110334:18"/>
day is the ſabbath of the Lord thy God, is morall, and containeth a perpetuall truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Doctor <hi>Whitguift</hi> [againſt <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright, page</hi> 553.] ſaith, <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou labour,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The meaning of which words is this, That ſeeing God hath admitted us ſix dayes to doe our own work in, we ought the ſeventh day to ſerve him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Muskulus</hi> [in his Book of <hi>common Places, fol.</hi> 60.] ſpeaking of the <hi>ſeventh day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Secondly, he apppointed the day, ſo that it ſhould not be at his peoples liberty: Six dayes (ſaith he) thou ſhalt doe all thy worke, but the ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God. So he doth eſpecially note, the dayes to worke, and he doth expreſſe that day, in which the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath ſhould be hallowed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Six dayes are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee, in which thou mayeſt work all things, touching thy ſelfe and thy own affaires; but the ſeventh day is not ſo: for that day is a great while agoe determined, and hallowed by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, unto reſt; and therefore that day ſhall not ſerve for thy workes, but thou ſhalt hallow him to the Lord thy God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Willet</hi> on the <hi>fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, [queſtion</hi> 13 <hi>pag.</hi> 360.] ſaith, <hi>God is ſaid to reſt, both that his reſt might be a monument of the Creation, perfected; and that God, by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, might induce us in like manner to reſt upon his Sabbaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:110334:18"/>Sixtly, <hi>Dod,</hi> and <hi>Clever, on the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> ſpeaking of the duty of the ſeventh day-Sabbath, in <hi>pag.</hi> 118. ſaith; <hi>The third reaſon is taken from Gods Example, &amp;c.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>If thou wilt follow Example, then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Example of the beſt. What Example can there be better, than God himſelf, who, when he made the World, reſted on the ſeventh day. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, from his Example, learne thou, that on the ſeventh day, thou give thy ſelfe to the duties of ſanctification, &amp;c.</hi> See <hi>pag.</hi> 119.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>Bayly</hi> (in <hi>Pract. Piety, page</hi> 255.) ſaith, <hi>To ſanctifie the Sabbath on the ſeventh day, is not a ceremoniall Law abrogated, but the Morall and Perpetuall Law perfected; So that (ſaith he) the ſame perpetuall Commandement which bound the Jewes to keepe the Sabbath on the ſeventh day, to celebrate the Worlds Creation, binds Chriſtians to ſolemnize the Sabbath on the ſeventh day. And in page</hi> 257. <hi>Therefore God planted this Commandement in the middeſt of the two Tables, becauſe the keeping of it, is the beſt help in keeping all the reſt. The conſcionable keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath, is the Mother of all Religion, &amp;c.</hi> And in <hi>pag.</hi> 259. ſaith, <hi>It is one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements which God ſpake with his own mouth, and twice wrote with his owne fingers, in Tables of ſtone, to ſignifie their Authority, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity. All that God wrote, were Morall and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110334:19"/>
perpetuall Commandements, and they are reckoned ten in number. If this were now an abrogated Ceremony, then there were but nine Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. And, in</hi> pag. 287. thus, <hi>The Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Law was injoyned to the</hi> Jewes <hi>only, and not to the</hi> Gentiles: <hi>But this Commandement of the Holy Sabbath (as Matrimony) was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God in the ſtate of innocency, when there was but one eſtate of men; therefore enjoyneth the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>aſwell as the</hi> Jewes: <hi>So that all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, all Houſe-holders, were commanded to conſtraine all ſtrangers, (as well as their own ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and familie) to obſerve the Holy Sabbath, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will forbeare to produce further Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of men, the <hi>Word, or Law of God,</hi> is ſufficient to teach the <hi>godly minded their duty;</hi> therefore obey it, and keep <hi>holy the Sabbath day,</hi> to wit, <hi>the ſeventh day,</hi> and not a ſeventh day, as many men doe thinke, that if they keepe a ſeventh day, they performe that duty which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of them by the Morall Law, although they keep not the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day ſucceſſively from the Creation, a great miſtake: For ſurely, as God hath not given men liberty to <hi>worſhip in what they pleaſe;</hi> neither hath God given them liberty to omit their duty of the ſeventh dayes reſt, and worſhip when they pleaſe; but they are to doe that when he hath appointed, and commanded it,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110334:19"/>
which indeed is the <hi>ſeventh day, called Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> the laſt day of the week; which day, <hi>God bleſſed and ſanctified,</hi> for men to performe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip on it, as hath been ſhewn. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour therefore it is, to ſay, <hi>we obey Gods Law,</hi> if we keep one day in ſeven, if it be not the ſeventh day, commanded in the Law. Againe, no man can account the firſt day of the week to be a ſeventh day, unleſſe men will <hi>preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly croſſe</hi> the order of Gods appointment, and overſlip the firſt day of the worlds Creation; and what warrant is there in Gods Word, for mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men ſo to doe, let all rationall men judge. Unleſſe men doe ſo, they cannot by any <hi>account</hi> conclude, that the firſt day of the week, is, or can be a ſeventh day; and <hi>therefore,</hi> in obſerving it for a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> they ſtand not firme to their own <hi>Principle, by keeping one day in</hi> 7. ſeeing it is the 8. day, in relation to the Creation, and therefore it cannot properly be ſaid to be one day in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. If men will refuſe to keep their Sabbath on the ſeventh day, which day, God hath <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and commanded by his holy Law,</hi> and will keep one day in ſeven, according to Gods place<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dayes in the week, and ſtand firm to their own <hi>Principle,</hi> then they are to keep the ſixth day of the week, called Friday, <hi>as Turkes doe,</hi> or elſe, ſome day or other before it, if the day be left to their owne choiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:110334:20"/>The Errour of this opinion may alſo thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: God <hi>commanded the Iſraelites</hi> to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe their <hi>male</hi> children on the eighth day, <hi>Gen</hi> 17.12. Had they obeyed Gods Law, and performed their duty, had they overſlipt the firſt day, and circumciſed the ninth, and accounted it for the eighth, (if neceſſity forced them not thereto,) certainely they had not, neither could they properly have ſaid, they <hi>Circumciſed</hi> one day in <hi>eight,</hi> nor the <hi>eighth day:</hi> Even ſo, it now ſtandeth with mens <hi>obſervation</hi> of the firſt day of the week, for the ſeventh day, which indeed in order from the Creation, is the eight; and therefore they which obſerve it, keep one day after <hi>ſeven,</hi> and not one day in <hi>ſeven.</hi> The like inſtance I will give, concerning the command of God, given to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> for their <hi>Eating of the Paſſeover on the fourteenth day of the firſt Month,</hi> Exod. 12. Had they eaten it the fifteenth day, whether had they obeyed Gods Law, where neceſſity hindreth not, certainly they had not: Even ſo it ſtandeth with mens obſerving the <hi>firſt day</hi> in ſtead of the <hi>ſeventh;</hi> or, <hi>Sunday,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Saturday.</hi> Let wiſe men take this into their conſideration, for, indeed, men doe deceive themſelves, to thinke they obey Gods Law, if they keep one day in ſeven, accounting it the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of the <hi>fourth Commandement,</hi> which thing indeed, is not in obſerving the firſt day of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110334:20"/>
week, which, according to <hi>godly order,</hi> is the eighth day, and therefore, <hi>mens practiſe</hi> in this particular, hath neither ſound, nor ſence, for to be the equitie of the <hi>fourth Commandement.</hi> If men will keep a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or day of reſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Equitie of the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement;</hi> then they are to keep it on the ſeventh day, <hi>which God commandeth, Exod.</hi> 20.8, 9, 10, 11. for, that indeed is the equitie of the fourth Commandement, and not keeping a day of reſt, either before, or after the ſeventh day; for men ſo to doe, is meer will-worſhip, a thing forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Apoſtle, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
               <p>Againe, we ſhall never finde in any of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, or Apoſtles writings, that ever the Law of the <hi>Sabbath was repealed;</hi> or, that ever it ſhould be transferred to the firſt day of the week; or, that ever the firſt day of the week was a <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, or ſhould be obſerved in ſtead of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> by Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Well ſaith Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> in this point, in the Doctrine of the <hi>Sabbath, pag.</hi> 24. <hi>ſec.</hi> 6. <hi>Our Saviour</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>oft times diſputed with the Phariſees of the * Sabbath day; and many times explained the meaning of that Commandement: But where is there any of the leaſt ſuſpition of his abrogating it? Where any mention that the Lords day was inſtituted in the place thereof.</hi> Well (ſaith he) <hi>Chriſt aſcended up on high, and left behind
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110334:21"/>
him his Apoſtles, and what did they? did they not keep the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Sabbath without noiſe, or ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and gladly teach the people congregated, on the Sabbath dayes. (* Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>Mark</hi> 2. <hi>Luke</hi> 6. <hi>Joon</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Anſwerable unto this, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>White,</hi> ſaith, <hi>On the Sabbath, the Apoſtles, and likewiſe many ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Apoſtles, for many ages, at leaſt</hi> 300. <hi>yeares, kept holy the Saterday of every week, in ſome Churches.</hi> Yea, <hi>Socrates lib.</hi> 6, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, <hi>That ſome Chriſtians after</hi> 400 <hi>yeares, obſerved the Sabbath weekly, with the firſt day of the weeke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> ſaith on <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Some men both godly and learned, are of an opinion, that the firſt day of the week, was appointed by the Apoſtles, for order ſake, &amp;c. It ſeemes,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a truth more probable, that every ſeventh day of the weeke, muſt, be ſet a part, in holy reſt, unto God, for this is the ſubſtance of the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That the ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath</hi> is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the time of the Goſpel, as it was in the time of the Law; I will briefly give <hi>five Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is, becauſe it was given to <hi>man,</hi> in his <hi>Innocency, Gen.</hi> 2.2, 3. and therein to all the <hi>world;</hi> to wit, to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as to the <hi>Jewes:</hi> this truth is confeſſed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:110334:21"/>
in his <hi>Annotations, Exod.</hi> 31.17. As alſo by <hi>Baily,</hi> in the <hi>Practice of Piety, pag.</hi> 258, 259. And alſo by <hi>Dod,</hi> on the <hi>fourth Commandement, pag.</hi> 125, 127.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe it is commanded by a divine and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive law, <hi>Exod</hi> 20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe <hi>God reſted</hi> on the ſeventh day, <hi>and bleſſed, and ſanctified it,</hi> for us to <hi>reſt,</hi> after his <hi>example, Exod.</hi> 20.11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.1.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Our Saviour kept the Sabbath, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16, 31. <hi>Mark</hi> 6.2. and we are to imitate him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.26. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.6.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> kept it, and other <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Acts</hi> 13.14, 15, 16, 37, 42, 43, 44, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.13, 14. <hi>chap.</hi> 17.2. and we are to imitate them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that doth this, and the ſonne of man which layeth hold on it, and keepeth the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, from polluting of it,</hi> Iſay 56.3, 4, 5, 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:110334:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Severall Authors produced, which affirme, the Church changed the Sabbath; and why they did it. <hi>2.</hi> Three Reaſons given, to manifeſt when it was done. <hi>3.</hi> Anſwers given to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall texts of Scripture, urged to prove the firſt day of the weeke, to be of a divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>4.</hi> Four Reaſons given, to manifeſt, it is not of a divine Inſtitution.</head>
               <p>EVident it is, that in ſome tract of time, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of the Apoſtles, the <hi>Romiſh Church layd aſide</hi> the duty of the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath,</hi> and obſerved the firſt day of the weeke, inſtead of it.</p>
               <p>Of this <hi>Socrates</hi> gives us notice, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>chap.</hi> 21. Where ſpeaking of Cuſtomes, he ſaith, <hi>Though in manner all Chriſtian Churches throughout the whole world, doe celebrate and receive the holy miſteries, every Sabbath day after other: Yet the people, inhabiting</hi> Alexandria, <hi>and</hi> Rome, <hi>of an old tradition doth not uſe it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Aegyptians <hi>adjoyning to</hi> Alexandria, <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Inhabitants of</hi> Thebaes, <hi>uſe to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate on the Sunday,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Brabourn,</hi> in the defence of the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:110334:22"/>
(againſt the ten <hi>Miniſters, page</hi> 481) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares out of the <hi>Centuries, Centure</hi> 4. <hi>chap.</hi> 6. <hi>page</hi> 477. layeth it down thus, <hi>There was no Eccleſiaſticall, or Church Aſſemblies at</hi> Rome, <hi>as there was at other Churches,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> [living in <hi>Rome,</hi> in the yeare 150.] <hi>Apol.</hi> 2. ſaith, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Sunday, all of us, aſſemble in the Congregation,</hi> &amp;c. See D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hylyn</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath, part.</hi> 2, <hi>chap.</hi> 2, <hi>ſect,</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Athenaſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>The obſervation of the Lords day, was taken up by a voluntary uſage in the Church.</hi> as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hylyn</hi> in his hiſtory on the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> declareth, <hi>part</hi> 2. <hi>chap,</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="5">5. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Perkins</hi> [on <hi>Gal,</hi> 4. <hi>verſe</hi> 10. ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſuperſtition of the <hi>popiſh Church,</hi> in obſervation of <hi>holy dayes</hi>] ſaith, <hi>Firſt, beſides the Lords day, they appointed many other Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths,</hi> &amp;c,</p>
               <p n="6">6. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Calvin</hi> [in his <hi>Inſtitutions, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>chap,</hi> 8. <hi>ſect,</hi> 33.] ſaith, <hi>The old Fathers, not without choyce of their owne, put in place of the Sabbath, the day we call Sunday,</hi> &amp;c. And a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after exhorteth us, <hi>to follow the order, by the Church apointed;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Bullenger</hi> [in his Book of <hi>godly Sermons, page</hi> 140.] ſaith, <hi>They of the Primitive Church did change the Sabbath day, leaſt peradventure, they ſhould have ſeemed to imitate the</hi> Jewes; <hi>and ſtill to have retained their orders, and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110334:23"/>
and made their aſſemblies and holy meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, on the firſt day of Sabbaths; (to wit) the firſt day of the weeke called Sunday.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>John Frith [Declare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Bapt. page</hi> 96] ſaith, <hi>Our Fathers which were in the beginning of the Church, did abrogate the Sabbath, to the intent, that Chriſtians might have an example of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty, and that they might know, that neither the keeping of the Sabbath, nor any other day is neceſſary: That a day ſhould be reſerved, in that the people might come together, to heare the Word of God; they ordained inſtead of the Sabbath, which was Saturdy, the next day following; and although they might have kept Saturday with the</hi> Jewes, <hi>as a thing indifferent; yet did they much better, to over ſet the day, to a perpetuall memory, that we are free and not bound to any day, but that we may doe any worke to the pleaſure of God, and the profit of our Neighbour,</hi> &amp;c. See D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>White</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath, page</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="9">9. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Tindals</hi> anſwer to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Moore, chap.</hi> 25. thus ſaith, <hi>We be Lords over the Sabbath, and may change it to munday, or any other day, as we ſee need; or may make every tenth day, holy day, if we ſee cauſe why; we may make two every weeke, if it were expedient, and one not enough to teach the people. Neither was there any cauſe to change it from the Saturday, then to put difference between us and the</hi> Jewes; <hi>leaſt we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110334:23"/>
ſervants to the day, after their ſuperſtition.</hi> As D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>White</hi> hath it, <hi>Ibid. page</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus</hi> on the <hi>Catti. part.</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 989. ſaith, <hi>The Apoſtolicall Church, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh its ſelfe from the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Synagogue,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hath, on good reaſon, made choyce of the firſt day,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="11">11. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Willet</hi> [in his <hi>Comment. on Exod. chap.</hi> 20. <hi>page</hi> 360.] ſaith, <hi>The Apoſtolique Church changed the holy day of reſt from the ſeventh day to the firſt, which is the Lords day, in remembrance of our redemption by Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. Dr. <hi>White,</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath, page</hi> 109. thus ſaith. <hi>Although the Sunday, or Lords day, in the time of the Law, was an ordinary working-day; yet in the time under the Goſpel, the ſame is an holy day, by a perpetuall Ordinance of the Catholique Church.</hi> And in <hi>pag.</hi> 212, he ſaith. <hi>It is apparent, that Chriſtian people made the Lords day of every week, an ordinary Holy-day, &amp;c. See alſo Dr.</hi> Prideaux <hi>on the Sabbath, pag.</hi> 24. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>I haſten, and ſhall take further occaſion, to manifeſt by larger <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> that the firſt day of the weeke is not of a Divine Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but an Ordinance of the Church: But firſt I will briefly deſcribe the time when it was done, as near as I can.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe, I have not met with any Author
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110334:24"/>
which hath pointed out the time, except Mr. <hi>Brabourne,</hi> who, in defence of the Sabbath, <hi>pag.</hi> 485. ſpeaking of the Counſell held at <hi>Laodicea, Anno</hi> 364. he ſaith, now the <hi>Sabbath began to be rejected, and the Lords day to be ſet up as the ſole Sabbath, without any other. Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Lords day muſt forſooth be preferred above the Sabbath, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> in his Expoſition on the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. moveth a queſtion, to know who changed the <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath;</hi> and then his anſwer is thus. <hi>It is commonly thought</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Jewiſh Sabbath was changed into the Lords day by Chriſtian Emperours, long after the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I doe not much diſſent from theſe mens ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, for there is much truth, no doubt, in both their expreſſions; yet I am not <hi>fully,</hi> of of their opinions, for, indeed I conceive it was firſt contrived, yea, and concluded on, incluſively, though not expreſſed, in the firſt Nicen Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, <hi>Anno</hi> 326. or thereabout, and my Reaſons are <hi>three.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>firſt Reaſon</hi> is, becauſe before that <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,</hi> there was not any <hi>Law,</hi> which commanded <hi>Chriſtians to keep the firſt day of the week,</hi> in performance of <hi>Religious worſhip;</hi> neither before that time were Chriſtians commanded to forbear labour on the Lords day. But this was done by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110334:24"/>
the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine his Edict,</hi> after the <hi>Counſell</hi> was diſſolved. <hi>Euſebius in the life of Conſtant. Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.19.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Reaſon is, becauſe after that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell was diſſolved, <hi>Conſtantine ſent an Edict to all Governours of Provinces in his Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, that they ſhould forthwith obſerve the Lords day, and honour Holy-daies, conſecrated to the memoriall of Martyrs, and ſolemnly obſerve the Feaſts of the Church,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">At this time, or a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is the time that <hi>Socrates</hi> ſpeaketh of lib. <hi>5.</hi> chap. <hi>21.</hi> ſaying, ſome deſpiſed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God, and made them cannons of their owne; they ſet at nought, and made no account of the law, publiſhed by the Apoſtles; ſo unadviſedly (ſaith he) they put in practiſe decrees contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the will of God himſelf.</note> 
                  <hi>Ibid. Chap.</hi> 23. Note, I doe not ſay the firſt day of the week was not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved till this time; for evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it is, it was obſerved by many Churches, in few years after the deceaſe of the Apoſtles. Yea, Dr. <hi>White</hi> on the Sabbath <hi>pag.</hi> 193. ſaith. <hi>The Vniverſall Church, before the decree of any Generall, or Nationall Counſell, made the Sunday, or Lords Day, a weekely Feſtivall.</hi> But I endeavour to denote, when it was that the Church rejected the Sabbath, and obſerved the firſt day of the week in ſtead of it.</p>
               <p>The third Reaſon why it is probable; the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down of the Sabbath, and the ſetting up of the firſt day of the week in ſtead of it, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived in the <hi>Nicen Councel,</hi> is, becauſe Chriſtians,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110334:25"/>
before that <hi>Counſell,</hi> were not forbid to obſerve the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath,</hi> nor threatned to bee <hi>Excommunicated</hi> if they did obſerve it; for that was not done till the <hi>Counſell held at Laodicea, Anno</hi> 364. which was about 38 yeares after the <hi>Nicen Councell,</hi> where they made a Law, that Chriſtians ſhould not <hi>Jewdize, and reſt upon the Sabbath day, but rather worke upon it, and that they ſhould prefer the Lords day above the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day; and, if any were found obſerving the Jewiſh Sabbath, they ſhould be excommunicated, or accurſed,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> hath it in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 482. Out of <hi>Hoſpine de Origen Faſt. Chap.</hi> 9 <hi>pag.</hi> 27. about this time many other <hi>Errours</hi> were ſet a foot; for, Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> in his forementioned Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 482. ſaith, you may read in Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> his <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Probleme, about the</hi> 300 <hi>and</hi> 400 <hi>years after Chriſt: Then began Images to creep into Churches; the Croſſe to be adored; Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints; praiers for the dead; Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; Purgatory; ſingle life of Miniſters; Monkery, and Monaſticall profeſſion, &amp;c.</hi> Thus have I ſhewn the time, or neere about, when the Lords holy ſeventh day-Sabbath was rejected, and the firſt day of the week inſtituted in its ſtead, which cauſeth me to ſay with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.126. <hi>It is time for thee Lord to worke, for they have made void thy Law.</hi> Yea,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110334:25"/>
it appeareth to me, to be a great cauſe of Gods Judgments on the World, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.4, 5.</p>
               <p>Lamentable it is, that the <hi>Learned of this Land,</hi> which <hi>profeſſe themſelvs to be guids to the blind, and lights of them which are in darkneſſe, and teachers of them which want knowledge, and to have the forme of knowledge, and truth of the Law,</hi> that they ſhould teach men to obſerve the firſt day of the week in ſtead of the ſeventh, contrary to the Law, upon a pretence that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> abrogated the Sabbath; and that he, and his Apoſtles inſtituted the firſt day of the week in its ſtead, when there is not any Word of God that teacheth either the one, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe there are many weak reaſons, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by many men, to prove their doctrine and practice;<note n="*" place="margin">Note, I pray, if it be not according to the words of the law and teſtimony, it is becauſe there is no light in them, <hi>Iſa. 8.20.</hi>
                  </note> both for the <hi>abrogation</hi> of the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> as alſo for <hi>manifeſting</hi> that the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the week <hi>is of a divine inſtitution,</hi> ſome principall places of <hi>Scripture</hi> produced, and <hi>perverted by them:</hi> I will briefly weigh and examine, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it to <hi>wiſe mens conſideration,</hi> and the <hi>Almighties bleſſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anti-ſabatharians</hi> ſay, <hi>Our Saviour to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the change of the Sabbath day, did plead for, and performe ſome things, that the</hi> Jewes <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110334:26"/>
the Sabbath might not doe:</hi> and to prove it they urge two Scriptures, the one <hi>Mark</hi> 2.23, 24. Where it is ſaid, our <hi>Saviours Diſciples, plucked the eares of Corne on the Sabbath day, and the Phariſes urged at our Saviour for that fact.</hi> Now ſay they, <hi>Our Saviour juſtified that fact, although it was a doing of that which the law of the Sabbath forbids,</hi> Ergo, <hi>the Sabbath was to be changed.</hi> Anſwer,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Saviour</hi> did not <hi>juſtifie</hi> them in that act, as an <hi>vnlawfull fact,</hi> but <hi>juſtified</hi> them in it as <hi>a lawfull</hi> or <hi>juſtifiable fact,</hi> as the <hi>cauſe ſtood</hi> with them, they being hungry, and that from <hi>a preſident in David,</hi> and thoſe that were with him, who in the <hi>like caſe did eat the ſhew bread,</hi> &amp;c. As alſo from that, <hi>Of the Prieſts in the Temple, which brake the Sabbath and were blameleſſe, Mat.</hi> 12.4, 5. which words of <hi>our Saviour doe imply, that had there not bene a neceſſity,</hi> their action had not been lawfull; but being a cauſe of neceſſity (as <hi>Davids, and the Prieſts was,</hi> the one having a relation to <hi>Charity,</hi> and the other to <hi>Piety) they were blameleſſe.</hi> And therefore in anſwer to the neceſſity of his Diſciples, our <hi>Saviour ſaid</hi> to his Adverſaries, <hi>If you had known what this meaned, I will have mercy and not ſacrifice,</hi> Math. 12 7. A <hi>repulſe</hi> to their <hi>cavill:</hi> And withall our <hi>Saviour</hi> cauſed them to know, that the <hi>ſonne of man is Lord,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110334:26"/>
alſo of the Sabbath.</hi> Which words of our Saviour doe imply, he being Lord of the Sabbath, knew the extent of the Sabbath better then they; for had they known the extent of the Sabbath, they would not have condemned the innocent, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.7. Let no man thinke, that our <hi>Saviour,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> or <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> did vouchſafe a diſpenſation to his Diſciples, to act that which was in its nature evill, for that he did not: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth thoſe words of our Saviour, in ſaying, he was <hi>Lord</hi> of the Sabbath, import, that he had <hi>changed</hi> the Sabbath, or would doe it. But thoſe words are to be underſtood far otherwiſe, and that very proper to.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Saviour</hi> may be <hi>rightly ſaid,</hi> to be <hi>Lord</hi> of the Sabbath, in a threefold reſpect.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that as he <hi>was God, Iohn</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. In which ſence, the Sabbath was made by him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect it was upheld by him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5 17. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>He is rightly ſaid, to be Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, in that he only</hi> holily kept it, in his perſon, for the perfecting of the Saints imperfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3, 4. <hi>chap,</hi> 10.4. Had our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour aboliſhed the <hi>law of the Sabbath,</hi> he had diminiſhed from the <hi>morall Law,</hi> which thing he did not, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17. For being man, <hi>and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, he was bound to keep the whole Law, Gal.</hi> 5.3. In which regard he was a <hi>ſubject</hi> to it,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110334:27"/>
and ſo he acknowledged himſelfe to be, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.7, 10. Yea, I ſay, <hi>It was impoſſible,</hi> that he could, or did <hi>diminiſh</hi> from the <hi>morall Law,</hi> in regard, circumciſed men were forbid ſo to doe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>chap.</hi> 12 32. It being ſo, I affirme, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth teach, or affirme, that Jeſus Chriſt did diminiſh from the holy law, the decalogue, doe charge our Saviour with ſinne, although they deſerue it not. But to defend his Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy therein, I doe affirme, <hi>our Saviour Chriſt did not before his death,</hi> nor at his <hi>death,</hi> nor by his <hi>reſurrection,</hi> diminiſh any precept of that Law, nor any part thereof: Therefore it followes, that we are as firmly, and as unchangeably bound to the obſervation of the ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath,</hi> as we are to any duty commanded in that <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſecond Scripture oft urged by them is, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. where mention is made of our <hi>Saviours</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Impotent man, and bidding him, <hi>take up his Bed and walke, verſe</hi> 18. It being the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day:</hi> a thing fordidden by the Law [as they ſay] therefore they infer, it manifeſted, that the Sabbath was, or ſhould be changed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Surely it is a very weake and ſlender ground to bear ſo weighty a matter: yea, ſo weake it is, that they know not well, what to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; ſomething they would have to prove their purpoſe, if they knew what; but ſurely there is nothing of any force to be gathered from thence,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110334:27"/>
to prove, that either the Sabbath was, or ſhould be abrogated; and therefore I paſſe over this Objection, as not worth the anſwering.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Anti-ſabatharians,</hi> to prove the change of the Sabbath, and to manifeſt the firſt day of the week to be of a divine inſtitution. They ſay, The <hi>Apoſtles aſſembled</hi> on the firſt day of the weeke, the day of our Saviours Reſurrection, and our Saviour honoured them with his preſence, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.19. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Sabbath was changed, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The inference is not to be proved by Scripture; the premiſes proveth not the thing intended, and therefore I ſay, not any of this doth prove the change of the Sabbath; nor that the firſt day of the week, is of a divine inſtitution, not in the leaſt. Neither did their aſſembling prove, that it was for the celebration of that day, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of any Grace that was brought to the <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>World,</hi> by the <hi>reſurrection of our Saviour</hi> from the dead, as ſome doe ſurmiſe, and that for two Reaſons.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, becauſe Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith [<hi>chap.</hi> 20.19.] That <hi>they aſſembled together for feare of the Iewes;</hi> had it been for any other end, doubtleſſe, he would have made it known unto us.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe when they aſſembled they knew not that he <hi>was riſen from the dead:</hi> no, neither did they believe the <hi>teſtimony of the Diſciples
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110334:28"/>
which Reported it to them</hi> after they were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16, 11. for which cauſe <hi>our Saviour reprehended them, v.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Our Saviour appearing to his diſciples after eight days, Joh. 20.26. is oft vrged to prove the change of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and that the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the weeke to be of a <hi>Divine Institution,</hi> but this helpeth to prove their purpoſe as the former; in regard, it was not upon the next firſt day as many do think: But it was upon ſome one day, after the firſt day of the week; had it been on the firſt day of the week that our Saviour appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Diſciples, it had been on the eighth day: But, St. <hi>John</hi> expreſly ſaith, it was after <hi>eight dayes,</hi> therefore not on the <hi>firſt day,</hi> which was the <hi>eighth day:</hi> It being ſo, this ſerveth not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe, to prove the abrogating of the ſeventh day-Sabbath; nor that the firſt day of the weeke is of a Divine Inſtitution, for performance of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Another Scripture urged to prove the firſt day of the week to be a ſet time for performance of publick worſhip, is, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. where it is ſaid, when the diſciples came together to break bread, upon the firſt day of the week, <hi>Paul preached</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This doth not prove the firſt day of the week to be of a <hi>Divine inſtitution,</hi> nor that their breaking of bread, was the <hi>communion of the Miſteries of the Lord in the Sacrament,</hi> ſeeing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110334:28"/>
it was an uſuall thing for the Diſciples to aſſemble together, <hi>to break bread daily, Acts</hi> 2.46. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.42.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Neither did the Apoſtles Ordination for Collection at <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Galatia,</hi> on the firſt day of the week, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. prove that the Churches then were to aſſemble on the firſt day of the week, to performe publique worſhip. Surely there is no ſuch word to be found in the Text, or elſewhere; but that which the Apoſtle did appoint in <hi>Corinth,</hi> and at <hi>Galatia,</hi> was, that every one, on the <hi>firſt day of the week,</hi> ſhould lay a part by himſelf, as God had proſpered him, &amp;c. Or this it may be read for our more proper under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Apoſtles meaning, <hi>upon one of the week daies, let every one of you lay apart by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp;c.</hi> Note, not at Church, there is no ſuch word; but at home: And ſo doth Mr. <hi>Tindall,</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> Tranſlate it: It being ſo, what doth this ſerve to prove, that all Chriſtian Churches, then, and ever ſince, were to aſſemble, for performance of publique worſhip, <hi>on the firſt day of the week;</hi> or, that thoſe words of the Apoſtles, did either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, or conſtitute it to be a Sabbath. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nothing at all; See Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. And alſo, Dr. <hi>Hylyns</hi> Hiſtory up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sabbath, <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did the Apoſtles, or Evangeliſts ever call the firſt day of the week, by name of a Sabbath, in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110334:29"/>
relation to a day of Reſt; nor when ever they ſpake of the firſt day of the week, they never cald it by the name of the Lords day, or Sunday: Had theſe Titles appertained to it, doubtleſſe they would not have been ſlack to have beſtowed them on it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To prove the Sabbath abrogated, Anti-Sabbatharians doe oft urge the Apoſtles words, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16.17. <hi>Let no man condemne you in meat, or in drink, or in reſpect of a Holy day, or of the New Moon, or of the Sabbath dayes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaketh not in this place of the ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath, Exod.</hi> 20.8. which our Saviour ratified, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. It being a part of the Morall Law; yea, and alſo commanded obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God by it incluſively, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37, 38. But of the Ceremoniall Sabbaths, forementioned; <hi>which were ſhadows of good things to come, as Meats, Drinks, and New Moons were, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboliſhed by Chriſt, became beggerly Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> Gal. 4.9. and fruſtrateth the work of Grace in the obſervers thereof, <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.4.</p>
               <p>Evident it is, theſe things there mentioned by the Apoſtle, were not written in Tables of ſtone, therefore, ſerveth not to prove the duty of the ſeventh day-Sabbath abrogated. Yea, I ſay, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, there is no appearance in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, that the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath</hi> was abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated by Chriſt, or ſhould be, after his death: Or,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110334:29"/>
that ever the firſt day of the weeke was <hi>inſtituted,</hi> or <hi>commanded,</hi> by him, or his Apoſtles, to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, for performance of publique worſhip: Neither did God, or Chriſt, ever ſanctifie that day to that end, as many doe imagine; nor never inſtituted, nor commanded his Church to obſerve it in ſtead of the Sabbath. Therefore, I ſay, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are not to preſume above what is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. what reaſon is there, that the firſt day of the week ſhould be held more high, and holy, than the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath, which God inſtituted, bleſſed, and ſanctified,</hi> and commanded us, and all men to obſerve, by the Morall Law: Yea, what reaſon is there, or, what word of God is there to be produced, to prove, that it is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to abſtain from common work on the firſt day of the week, called Sunday? As alſo, that we ought to doe common work on the ſeventh day-Sabbath, called Saturday. Deceive not thy ſelf, nor let any man deceive thee, or cauſe thee to believe, that it was the practice of Chriſtian Churches, to aſſemhle every firſt day of the week, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form publique worſhip, in the Apoſtles dayes, for that they did not. Yea, I ſay, it is not to be proved by Scripture, that ever any one Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, did three times aſſemble ſucceſſively, to perform publique worſhip on the firſt day of the week, called Sunday: Yea, I ſuppoſe, that not any <hi>Anti-Sabbatharian</hi> can prove, that ever
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110334:30"/>
any one Congregation did aſſemble two firſt days ſucceſſively, in the Apoſtles daies; or, that ever it was by them eſteemed more holy, or more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, than any other of the 6 daies. Yet, I ſay, what if it could be proved, that any Congregation in the Apoſtles days, did aſſemble 6 firſt days ſucceſſively to perform worſhip on it; yet it would not prove the <hi>ſeventh day-Sabbath</hi> abrogated; nor, that the firſt day of the week was deſigned for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Worſhip, ſeeing Chriſtians in thoſe daies, did daily aſſemble, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.46. <hi>Ch.</hi> 5.42. Yea, I ſay, if ſuch a thing could be proved, (which none can doe) it would bind us no more to the conſtant performance of the former, than of the latter.</p>
               <p>That the firſt day of the week is not of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution, nor is to be obſerved as a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, I will give 3. Reaſons.</p>
               <p>The firſt Reaſon is; Becauſe if men keep the firſt day of the week for a Sabbath, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day for a working day, it is to doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly againſt a Precept, both Affirmative, and Negative, <hi>Exod,</hi> 20.8, 9, 10.</p>
               <p>Secondly; It cannot be, that the firſt day of the week, is an Ordinance of the Goſpel; becauſe then, the preaching of Faith, would make void the Law, contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31.</p>
               <p>Thirdly; The firſt day of the week cannot be of a Divine Inſtitution, becauſe then the Law,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110334:30"/>
which commandeth the ſeventh dayes reſt, would croſſe the Goſpels Inſtitution, contrary to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.31.</p>
               <p>I need not to inſiſt to give more reaſons, to prove that the firſt day of the week is not of a Divine Inſtitution, ſeeing the truth is plentifully confeſſed by many wiſe, and learned men, whoſe underſtandings are not eclipſed with errour in this particular. Yea, I ſay, Papiſts themſelves, doe confeſſe, the obſervation of the Sunday is not to be proved by the written word of God; and therefore, oftentimes in their writings, they urge at Proteſtants, becauſe they cry Scripture, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to be the Rule of their Faith, and Practice, in the way of Religion, when they obſerve the firſt day of the week, which is called Sunday, in ſtead of the Sabbath, called Saturday, when there is no Word of God to prove, that ſo they ought to doe.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians ought to make the Word of God the Rule of their Faith, and Life, and not the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men, though never ſo ancient, or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally received; no, nor the ſayings of Men, though wiſe, grave, and learned, <hi>if they ſpeake</hi> not according to the <hi>Law</hi> of God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.10. and therefore good it is for every one which loveth truth, and hateth errour, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Councel of <hi>Gracehop</hi> (placed at the Beginning of the Bible, Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1603.)
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110334:31"/>
who ſaith; <hi>Refuſe all ſence of Scripture, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Firſt and Second Tables of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi> Imbrace his Counſell, for it is good, it tendeth to further men in the way of Godlineſſe; for certainly, mens well meaning, or acting in the way of Religion, will not ſtand them in ſtead, to bring them into acceptation with God, except it be in the way that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of them, for he will not accept of any worſhip, or ſervice, which he hath not appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or commanded, <hi>Numb.</hi> 1. to 41. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.18.19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.3.4. <hi>Mark</hi> 7.6.7.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20, 21, 22. And therefore, <hi>It is not every one that ſaith, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heaven; but he that doth the will of my Father,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21.</p>
               <p>Had men that due reſpect to the Law of God, as is meet, there would not be any need to uſe Scripture Arguments and Reaſons to move them to the obedience thereof; or to manifeſt, they are not to walke in a way contrary to it, as men doe, in obſerving the firſt day in ſtead of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, out of a blind Devotion, through a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſion, that it is a Goſpel-Ordinance, when indeed it is not, but a meer humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, or Eccleſiaſticall Inſtitution, or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Tradition; and to manifeſt the truth thereof, I will produce the teſtimony of ſeverall Authors, for an addition to the former, which affirme the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:110334:31"/>
               <p n="13">13. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Whitguift</hi> againſt <hi>Cartwright, page</hi> 553. citeth the words of Saint <hi>Aguſtine (ad Romana Janu)</hi> Thus, <hi>that the Paſſion of Chriſt and his Reſurrection [note, that is the firſt day of the weeke] and the day of the comming down of the holy Ghoſt is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not celebrated by any command writen, but by the determination of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. In the <hi>Harmony of Confeſſions,</hi> I finde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many <hi>notable</hi> expreſſions of this nature, in <hi>page</hi> 479. is ſaid, <hi>We ſee, that in ancient Churches, there were not only ſet houres for meetings, but that alſo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the latter confeſſion of <hi>Helvetia.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>even the Lords day, ever ſince the Apoſtles time, was conſecrated to religious exerciſe,</hi> &amp;c <hi>We doe celebrate and keepe the Lords day, and not the Sabbath, and that of a free obſervation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15 Out of the <hi>Confeſſion of Auſpurge, page</hi> 493. in their fourth <hi>Article,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> about holy dayes, ſaith, <hi>Of which ſort is, the Lords day, the Nativity, Paſſover, and the reſt, &amp;c.</hi> And again, thus, <hi>becauſe it was neceſſary to appoint a certain day, that the people might know when to come together: It ſeemes that the Church for that purpoſe, did appoint the Lords day,</hi> &amp;c. Look the firſt obſervation on the <hi>Confeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>White</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath [page</hi> 242.] ſpeaking of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Immediately
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110334:32"/>
after them, it is apparent, the Chriſtian people made the Lords day of every weeke, an ordinary Feſtivall.</hi> See alſo <hi>page</hi> 217, and in <hi>page</hi> 218. he ſaith, Conſtantine, <hi>among many other religious conſtitutions, he ordained the weekly Sabbath of the Lords day,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="17">17. The tranſlator of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Predeaux</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> in his Preface, doth affirm, <hi>that</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet <hi>one of the four Profeſſours in</hi> Leyden, <hi>doth affirm, that the appointing of the Lords day for Gods publicke ſervice, was neither done by God himſelfe, nor by his Apoſtles, but by the authority of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hylyn</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Emperour</hi> Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine <hi>was the firſt that made any law for the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lords day:</hi> ſee his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath, part.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1. And again, <hi>ibid. part.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. ſpeaking of Chriſt and of the Sabbath, ſaith, <hi>Neither did Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, ordain another Sabbath inſtead of this; as if they had intended, onely to ſhift the day, and to transferre this honour to another time; their doctrine and their practice, are directly contrary to ſo new a fancy. It is true</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in ſome tract of time, the Church; in honour, to his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, did ſet apart that day, on which he roſe, to holy exerciſe; but this on their own authority, and without any warrant from above, that we heare of.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:110334:32"/>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>Muskulous</hi> in his Book of <hi>Common places, fol.</hi> 66. thus ſaith, <hi>We Chriſtian men leaving the</hi> Jewes <hi>Sabbath, doe keepe our holy reſt upon the firſt day,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Know alſo what the originall <hi>Actors,</hi> or <hi>Authors,</hi> of <hi>changing the Lords holy Sabbath</hi> to the firſt day of the week, in the <hi>Remiſh Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> on <hi>Apocalips chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 10. ſaith, <hi>If the Church had authority and inſpiration from God, to make Sunday (being a working day) an everlaſting holy day; and the Saturday, which was before a holy day, now a common working day: Why may not the ſame Church preſcribe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the other Feaſts.</hi> Eaſter, Whitſuntide, Chriſtmas <hi>and the reſt, for the ſame warrant ſhe had for the one, that ſhe had for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I need not produce larger teſtimony, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate who it was, that aboliſhed the <hi>Lords</hi> ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath,</hi> or who it was, that inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the firſt day of the week in its ſtead; but that which is already ſaid, doth ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, who were the <hi>originall Authors of it, and of all other ſuperſtitious holy dayes, to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God,</hi> and the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the world, without Gods eſpeciall and abundant mercy. <hi>But bleſſed be God, we have yet time to fly unto the Lord for mercy, and to conforme our ſelves to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110334:33"/>
the obedience of his will, and let it be our comfort he is abundantly pardonfull,</hi> Iſa. 55.6.7. <hi>James</hi> 1.21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To be ſhort,</hi> as it is well known, the <hi>Church changed the Sabbath to the firſt day of the weeke,</hi> ſo alſo it is known and acknowledged, the Church hath power to change the day to ſome other day. For, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Prideaux</hi> in his Book of the <hi>Sabbath, page</hi> 34. affirmes, that <hi>Calvin, Bullinger, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerius Brentius, Chimnitius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the reformed Churches, ſtill affirmes, the Church hath power to change the Lords day to ſome other day.</hi> Yea, happy ſhall the Church be, that worſhippeth God according to his Law, and giveth him his due, by placing on the ſeventh day, the honour which God requireth to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on it, which hath been taken from it this 1300. yeares: for greatly hath God been diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by mens conſecrating the firſt day of the week, to be a holy reſt inſtead of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> ſeeing God never inſtituted it, nor commanded it to be: and therefore, I ſay, with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Prideaux</hi> [on the <hi>Sabbath, page</hi> 22, <hi>ſect.</hi> 7.] <hi>The inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords day, out of the Scripture, either expreſly, or by neceſſary conſequence, ſhew me he that can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As I have diſavowed, <hi>That the honour due to God on the ſeventh day-Sabbath,</hi> to be placed on the firſt day of the week, called <hi>Sunday,</hi> or <hi>Lords
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110334:33"/>
day,</hi> (or <hi>Sabbath,</hi> as mens opinions leads them) So I doe diſavow the Title of the Lords day, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to belong to the firſt day of the week, and therefore I ſay, very improperly are the words of St. <hi>John, Revel.</hi> 1.10. applied to it, for there is no ſuch thing there manifeſted in the Text, that the Apoſtle had any ſuch meaning. Yea, I ſay, there is no more reaſon that that Title ſhould be given to the firſt day of the week, the day of our Saviours Reſurrection, than to the day of his Birth, Death, or Aſcenſion, unleſſe becauſe it was anciently given to it; or elſe, becauſe men will have ſomething to credit that which they will have Honourable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignatius, calling it by the name of the Lords Day,</hi> proves not, that that Title is due to it by a <hi>Divine inſtitution,</hi> no more than his bringing in of <hi>Anthemes</hi> into the Church, doth prove that it was of a <hi>Divine inſtitution, Socrat. Lib.</hi> 6 <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Yea, I ſay, there is more reaſon to be given, that St. <hi>John</hi> meant the ſeventh day of the week, rather than the firſt, becauſe it was knowne by name the Lords day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.11. But the firſt day of the week was never knowne by that name: Yet, I doe not ſay, that St. <hi>John</hi> ſpake of that day neither; but of the day of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or time of his <hi>Reign</hi> in Power and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or of the day, or time of Judgment, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:110334:34"/>
2.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.5. who being in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſaw it in his Viſion, as if the day had been preſent.</p>
               <p>What if the <hi>Roman Church</hi> hath, and doth obſerve the firſt day of the week, in remembrance of our Saviours Reſurrection, as they doe the <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> in remembrance that he was betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the <hi>Friday,</hi> in remembrance of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Ought we therefore to follow their vain <hi>Idolatrous cuſtome and tradition</hi> in theſe things? Oh no, we ought not; for certainly, God doth not require theſe things at our hands, neither by Law, nor Goſpel.</p>
               <p>If this, which hath been ſaid in this Subject, will not ſatisfie men, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is our duty to reſt the ſeventh day, <hi>to wit,</hi> Saturday; and worſhip God on it, which is Gods Sabbath, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.9, 10, 11. As alſo, that it is our duty to work the firſt day of the week, called Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; let it be proved either by Law, or Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that it is our duty to work Saturday, and to reſt Sunday. If this, none can doe, I affirme, to the honour of God, and the advancement of his Holy Law; and for the beating off of all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, and ungodly intrenching upon the Lords Holy Sabbaths; and for the awaking of all thoſe out of errour, which would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly periſh in it; and to reduce all that love Gods Law, to the due obedience of it. I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110334:34"/>
that it is as great a ſinne, to obſerve the firſt day of the week, in ſtead of the ſeventh; as it is to worſhip an Image, in ſtead of the true God: For, to doe the one, is contrary to the Second Commandement of Gods Law; and, to doe the other, is contrary to the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the ſame Law: It being ſo, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire my Brethren, my Friends, yea, and all men, to conſider of this, (which condemneth Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and yet juſtifieth themſelves in a <hi>weekly trangreſſion</hi> of the <hi>Lords ſeventh day-Sabbaths</hi>) that they may <hi>ceaſe to doe evill, and learn to doe well,</hi> Iſa. 1.16, 17. For, their obtaining of grace here, and glory hereafter: For, <hi>the worke of Righteouſneſſe is Peace, and the effect of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, is quietneſſe, and aſſurance for ever,</hi> Iſa. 32.17. And ſo I conclude with the ſaying of <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13, 14.</p>
               <p>Let us heare the concluſion of all, <hi>Fear God, and keep his Commandements;</hi> it is the whole duty of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:110334:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> A refutation of the opinion of thoſe, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, there is no Sabbath day, whereon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are to abſtain from corporall labour. As alſo their ſaying, that holy walking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, is the keeping of the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</head>
               <p>I Shall not need to be large in this particular, by reaſon I have already proved, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth <hi>day,</hi> to wit, <hi>Saterday,</hi> is the <hi>Sabbath</hi> which <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought to keep <hi>holy</hi> to the <hi>Lord,</hi> and to abſtain from ſervill work on it: therefore I ſhall be brief.</p>
               <p>Theſe men following the generall <hi>notion,</hi> that the ſeventh day-<hi>Sabbath</hi> is abrogated; and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other day inſtituted in the new Teſtament, in its ſtead, for a day of publick worſhip, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all dayes are alike to thoſe that are in Chriſt, and no one day to be obſerved above another; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> affords them ſuch a <hi>liberty, Rom.</hi> 14.6. From whence they infer, they are not oblieged to the obſervation of the ſeventh dayes-<hi>Sabbath,</hi> but that they have liberty to doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon work thereon. Great is their errour herein, the Lord diſcloſe it unto them; for, doubtleſſe,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110334:35"/>
the Apoſtles meaning was farre from theirs, for they ſhall <hi>never be able to prove,</hi> that ever the Apoſtle gave Chriſtians liberty to walk in diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the <hi>morall law,</hi> the <hi>docalogue.</hi> And therefore it cannot be, that where the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>he that obſerveth a day, obſerveth it to the Lord, and he that obſerveth not the day, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it not to the Lord:</hi> That he ſpake of rhe ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath,</hi> there is not a word of any ſuch thing, nor any ſound of any ſuch meaning, that the Apoſtle had. And therefore it muſt be, that he ſpake of obſerving a day, for acting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or indifferent things; and not in keeping the Sabbath, or not keeping of it, and that for the <hi>avoiding of theſe abſurdities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath</hi> be abrogated, and no other day of reſt inſtituted in its ſtead; then there is one holy day leſſe then God in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning inſtituted, and one working day more; a very abſurd thing, for any ſo to affirme. Yea, that which followeth thereon is worſe: <hi>viz.</hi> That God is leſſe mercifull to man and beaſt, ſince our <hi>Saviour ſuffered death,</hi> then he was before: In that before he ſuffered death, hee afforded man and beaſt, a day of reſt, to refreſh their bodies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their weariſome and toylſome labour. And ſince he came and ſuffered death, he hath not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded them any at all. Theſe things ſuiteth not with Gods ordering providence; therefore
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110334:36"/>
to ſay, there is no day of reſt, is an errour.</p>
               <p>Theſe men doe alſo apprehend, the ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath</hi> figured out to us, faith in Chriſt, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.3. becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We which have believed doe enter into reſt.</hi> From whence they conclude, that when men beleeve, they have that ſanctification in Chriſt, of which the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> was a ſigne. If it be granted, or if it could be proved, that the ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath,</hi> was a ſigne of our <hi>ſanctification in Chriſt.</hi> It will not therefore follow, that when men beleeve, they are diſcharged from the duty of obſerving it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it can be proved a ceremoniall precept alſo; the reaſon is, becauſe a ſign properly, or ſimply differeth from a ceremony, and that ſhall thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
               <p>Ceremoniall <hi>Sabbaths</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23 &amp; <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16, 17. which God gave to the <hi>Iſralites,</hi> to be a ſigne, that the Lord ſanctified them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.12. being ſignes and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, was taken away by Chriſt, and nailed to his Croſſe: of this kinde of ſignes was Circumciſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. and the Paſſover, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.13. But ſignes which were not ceremoniall, being given of <hi>God,</hi> remaineth to the end of the world, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.14. <hi>chap.</hi> 9.13. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.29. And in this ſence, indeed, the ſeventh <hi>dayes-Sabbath</hi> is a ſigne, <hi>Exod</hi> 31.17. But not as a ſigne, in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to a figurative ceremony.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:110334:36"/>Again, the ſeventh <hi>dayes-Sabbath,</hi> which was given to be a ſigne, that God made Heaven and Earth in ſix dayes, &amp;c. was wrought in Tables of ſtone. But the Sabbath, which was given to be a ſigne, that the Lord ſanctified them, was not. Therefore, although theſe Sabbaths were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogated, it is no argument to prove, the other was abrogated alſo.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Theſe men which will have no Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath in that ſence, which the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement requireth; namely, to abſtaine from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile labour on the ſeventh day, doe apprehend, <hi>their ceaſing from ſinne, and growing in grace e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, is the true keeping of the Chriſtian Sabbath, and not ceaſing from labour any one day, if it cannot with conveniency be omitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I doe very well approve of a holy walking every day, both for mortifying of ſin, and grouth in godlineſſe; and doe heartily deſire, there may be a daily progreſſe therein by us all. But I muſt tell them, as the truth is, their holy devotion in the way they intend, doth not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge them of any duty that God requirerh of them by his Holy Law, the Decalogue, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling I am that they ſhould know it to. And therefore I deſire to know of them, whether Gods people, before Chriſt ſuffered death, were not to walke holy every day as well as we? If yea, as doubtleſſe they did. But had they omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110334:37"/>
the duty of the ſeventh dayes reſt, could they have been ſaid to have walked holy every day? Oh no, they could not. Even ſo it ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with men ever ſince our Savtours death; for, the ſame Law which bound the Iſraelites to keep a holy reſt on the ſeventh day, bindeth Chriſtians now, as hath been ſhewn, <hi>pag.</hi> 34. 35. Therefore, ſurely men doe deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to thinke they walk holy every day, when they doe directly contrary to the Law of God on the ſeventh day. Yea, I ſay, albeit they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find any of the ancient ſix working dayes inſtituted, nor commanded in the Goſpel to be a day for performance of publick worſhip; yet they may find Gods ancient Sabbath in the Law, where he commandeth them to keep the ſeventh day holy unto the Lord, whereon they are not to doe ſervile work, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, I deſire that we may imploy it in his worſhip and ſervice, and not after our owne wills, either for pleaſure, or profit; but that we <hi>call the Sabbath a delight, to conſecrate it as glorious to the Lord, and honour him, not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our owne wayes, nor ſeeking our owne wills, nor ſpeaking a vaine word.</hi> This is the Sabbath to be obſerved, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. And this let us doe; for, <hi>whoſoever keepeth the whole Law, and fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in one point, is guilty of all,</hi> Jam. 2.10, 11. Mat. 5.19. Yea, certaine it is, <hi>Whoſoever turneth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110334:37"/>
away his eare from hearing the Law, his Prayer ſhall be abominable.</hi> Prov. 28.9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>A Concluſion to the Work.</head>
               <p>TO reſiſt the duty of the ſeventh <hi>day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> which God requireth by the fourth <hi>Commandement.</hi> Be not of thoſe which ſay, the Law of Gods ten <hi>Commandements</hi> is not given to the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> Nor of thoſe which ſay, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath abrogated the whole <hi>Law:</hi> Nor of thoſe which confeſſe, the morality of the 1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. and denyeth the morality of the fourth: Nor of thoſe which ſay, every day is a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and keep no <hi>Sabbath</hi> at all: Neither ſay thou, what a ſtir is heare about the obſervation of a ſeventh day; as if peace here, and glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, did conſiſt in a corporall abſtaining from la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour on the ſeventh day; and ſo put off a duty which highly concerneth Gods honour, and thy owne ſalvation. Therefore know, the duty which thou oweſt to God, is not onely an abſtaining from <hi>corporall labour</hi> on the ſeventh day; But alſo an abſtaining from all <hi>actions, contrary to the law of God:</hi> as alſo a holy conſecrating it to his ſervice, by <hi>worſhipping him</hi> on it, in ſpirit and truth, as <hi>God by the Goſpel</hi> requireth of thee:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110334:38"/>
Therefore be not haſty to reject the duty of the ſeventh <hi>day-Sabbath,</hi> which <hi>God by his holy Law requireth of thee:</hi> Neither ſtudy to raiſe up <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections</hi> againſt it, leaſt thou be found a fighter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; and alſo become like unto the Scribes and Phariſes, ſpoken of <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.13. which <hi>ſhut up the Kingdome of Heaven before men, &amp; refuſe to go in themſelves, nor ſuffer them that would enter to come in:</hi> But be of thoſe which have reſpect to all Gods <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> and of thoſe which have walked in all the <hi>Commandements</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>God</hi> without reproof, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. Love Gods Law as the Prophet did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.77, 97. and delight in it as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> did, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22. and obtaine bleſſedneſſe, [<hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.14.] to <hi>juſtification, Rom.</hi> 3.13. <hi>through faith, chap.</hi> 3.33. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6.</p>
               <p>Finally, There are many men which thinke they know much of God in the Goſpel; and that they obſerving what Jeſus Chriſt requireth of them by it; they performe what duties ſoever God requireth of them by the Law; and indeed ſo they did, if they did rightly underſtand the duties, which Jeſus Chriſt by the Law, requireth of them; but in that they doe not, verily, they come ſhott of the duty of obſervation of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth <hi>dayes-Sabbatb,</hi> commanded in the firſt Table of Gods Law: The duties of which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110334:38"/>
Table, our <hi>Saviour</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37. compriſeth into one Commandement, and in requiring obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God by it, he doth as ſtrictly command obedience to the ſeventh day-Sabbath, the duty commanded in the fourth Commandement, as he doth require performances to the duties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded either in the 1, 2, or 3. commandements of that Law; ſee alſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18, 19. <hi>Chap</hi> 19.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>James</hi> 2.10. Therefore let no man think, that by his love to Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, he doth fulfill the Law in that way ſpoken of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>If he refuſe to perform that duty to God, which Ieſus Chriſt in the Goſpel requireth of him by the Law, (in ſome meaſure:) For, doubtleſs our obedience to the Commandements of God, is the fruit of true love, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.15.21. compared with <hi>Ch.</hi> 10.30. For thus ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>This is the love of God, that we keep his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.3. <hi>which thing Ieſus Chriſt did, Joh.</hi> 15.10. Yea, and we are to <hi>imitate him therein,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.17. <hi>And he that ſo doth, in him dwelleth the love of God perfect indeed,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.5. <hi>But he that ſaith he knoweth God, and kepeth not his Commandements, is a lyar,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.10. <hi>What union and communion there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Law and the Goſpel,</hi> ſee <hi>page</hi> 20. <hi>And he that walketh in that union, dwelleth in God, and God in him; and ſuch a one brings
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110334:39"/>
forth the fruit of the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 5.22. <hi>And where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is libertie,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.17. <hi>And againſt ſuch there is no Law to condemn him,</hi> Rom. 8.1. For indeed it was not made to that end, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. But yet they are not delivered from the obedience of it, but injoyned to it, <hi>Mat,</hi> 19.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1.2.3.5. <hi>James</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. But indeed the Law is made for the lawleſſe, and diſobedient; for the ungodly, and for ſinners; for unholy, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, as namely, for <hi>Anti-no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians,</hi> and <hi>Anti-Sabbatharians,</hi> and all <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines,</hi> which will be above Ordinances, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> make their boaſt, they have nothing to doe with the Law, nor the Law with them. I ſay, (as the Scriptures teach) for ſuch men the Law was made, and it hath dominion over them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they will not beleeve it, yet ſurely they will know it, if they repent not of ſetting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt it, and refuſe to conforme to the obedience of it, as Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37. for their avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of wrath, and obtaining of mercy through faith.</p>
               <p>I am ſorry for their deluſions, and ſhall not ceaſe to pray for their converſion; <hi>That their ſinnes may be blotted out, when the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> That they may be made partakers of that purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110334:39"/>
felicity, by the merit of Jeſus Chriſt, through faith; which hath life without death; peace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble, and joy without ſorrow: which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable bleſſedneſſe, I deſire may be confirmed on all thoſe which love Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This alſo know, <hi>I am no Jew,</hi> nor inclined to any <hi>Jewiſh opinions;</hi> I ſeek not righteouſneſſe by the Law, but by <hi>faith in the Son of God,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Goſpel.<note n="*" place="margin">Thoſe opinions are Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, which lead men to ſeeke Juſtification by the works of the Law, or, by obſerving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogated precepts, or Jewiſh cuſtomes, or traditions of their inventions; none of theſe I owne, as being of God, or from God. But, as for the fourth Commandement, by which God requireth obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the ſeventh day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, being one of the ten mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall precepes, is of God, and from God, and to obſerve it, is no more Jewiſh, than to obſerve the duties command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God, in the <hi>1, 2,</hi> or <hi>3.</hi> commandements of that Law</note> Yet, I know, I cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine righteouſneſs by the Goſpel, if I walke contrary to the expreſs duties which God by his Law requireth of me; the reaſon is, becauſe there is no way to bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, contrary to the way of righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31.32, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17. which is the Law of Gods Ten Commandements. But if thou knoweſt a way to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſalvation without it, or contrary to it, declare it: But, if this thou canſt not doe, then conforme to all duties commanded by it, and neglect it not, and have not any diſ-reſpect to any truth in this Subject declared by me, becauſe of any perſonall
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110334:40"/>
failing which thou maiſt perceive in me: But this know, it is in me the manifeſtation of the words of truth, made known by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. <hi>That God hath choſen the fooliſh things of this world, to confound the wiſe. &amp;c. and the things that are not, to bring to naught the things that are; for the fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer than men, and the weakneſſe of God is ſtronger than men,</hi> verſ. 25. <hi>That no fleſh may glory in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> verſ. 29.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>All Praiſe to God.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list_of_authors_cited">
            <pb facs="tcp:110334:40"/>
            <head>The Authors cited in this TREATISE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Iuſtin Martyr.</item>
               <item>Athanaſius.</item>
               <item>Euſebius</item>
               <item>Socrates Scholaſt.</item>
               <item>Auguſtine.</item>
               <item>Calvin.</item>
               <item>Tremelius.</item>
               <item>Tindall.</item>
               <item>Bucer.</item>
               <item>Brentius.</item>
               <item>Chimnetius</item>
               <item>Muskulus.</item>
               <item>Beza.</item>
               <item>Bullenger.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Perkins.</item>
               <item>Centuries.</item>
               <item>The Confeſsion of the Church of Helvetia.</item>
               <item>The Confeſsion of Auſpurgh.</item>
               <item>Vrſinus.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Frith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Whitgift.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Gracehop.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Ainſworth.</item>
               <item>Dod &amp; Clever.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Bayly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Prideaux,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Revert.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Brabourne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Willet.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> White</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Hyling.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Biſco,</item>
               <item>The Rhemiſt Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:110334:41"/>
            <head>A Table to find the principall points contained in this Treatiſe. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN pages 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</hi> is manifeſted, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Decalogue is morall, and bindeth Gentiles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> well as Jewes, to the duties therein expreſſed.</p>
            <p>In <hi>pages 8, 9, 10.</hi> are <hi>12</hi> abſurdities, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> follow on the Aſſertion, that the fourth command<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, or part thereof, is abrogated.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>12 page</hi> to the <hi>35.</hi> is manifeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, that the obſervation of the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> day-Sabbat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is morall, and we are injoyned to the duty of it.</p>
            <p>In <hi>pages 36, 37, 38, 39.</hi> is manifeſted, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Church changed the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> day-Sabbath to the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> day of the week, and why they did it.</p>
            <p>In <hi>pages 40, 41, 42,</hi> is manifeſted the time whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Church changed it, or neere about.</p>
            <p>From <hi>page 43.</hi> to <hi>52.</hi> is manifeſted, that our S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viour Chriſt did not abrogate the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> day-Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bath: As alſo, that the firſt day of the week is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of a divine inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pages 59, 60, 61.</hi> manifeſteth, that the Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of the Lords day appertaineth not to the firſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the week.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pages 63, 64.</hi> manifeſteth, that every day is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Sabbath.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
